<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The penitent bandito, or, The history of the conversion &amp; death of the most illustrious lord, Signor Troilo Sauelli, a baron of Rome by Sir T.M.</title>
            <author>Biondi, Giuseppe, 1537-1598.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2936B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1232_CANCELLED</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11207633</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11207633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39290</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39290)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1807:4, 1428:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The penitent bandito, or, The history of the conversion &amp; death of the most illustrious lord, Signor Troilo Sauelli, a baron of Rome by Sir T.M.</title>
                  <author>Biondi, Giuseppe, 1537-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, more correct.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>144, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Blondo by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Errata sheet following contents at end.</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing P1232 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.) at reel 1428:09.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Savelli, Troilo, d. 1592.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39290:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Penitent Bandito:</hi> Or the HISTORY Of the Converſion &amp; Death of the moſt Illuſtrious Lord <hi>Signor Troilo Sauelli,</hi> a Baron of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition more correct.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>T. M.</hi> Knight.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Matth. 20.16.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sic erunt noviſſimi primi.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>MDCLXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:39290:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:39290:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Hiſtory</hi> following has been tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, though not at all into ours, nor yet ſo carefully, into others, out of the true Original <hi>Italian,</hi> as I could have wiſhed. The differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces between the Copies,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39290:3"/>which walk up and down the world, are not great; ſaving that when there is queſtion of truth; and that, concerning a noble ſubject; and the ſame, accompanied with variety of natural, and lively circumſtances, I cannot find in my heart, to let any difference go for ſmal. I have therefore, at once, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken both pains, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to draw ſtore of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies into my hand, and it has not been without ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. For, if I have not laid hold upon the very <hi>Original,</hi> which was written by the Relator himſelf; I dare ſay, I am grown very neer it, and that it is preciſely true. And this <hi>Elogium</hi> I will be bold to give the Diſcourſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39290:3"/>we have in hand that it has been read in ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries with extream avidity. Nay, perhaps there has not iſſued, in many of theſe laſt Ages, any one hiſtorical <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> of a particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, the conſideration whereof, has more often been attended by tears, then this.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The birth, perſon, and parts of this Noble Man.</note>The Perſon whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns was a <hi>Baron</hi> of <hi>Rome, Sig. Troile Sauelli,</hi> a branch, ſprung up from a root of as noble blood, as a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain extraction from the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Romans,</hi> could tell how to make it. His perſon, and the parts of his generous mind, are beſt deſcribed in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> it ſelf, ſo that, I will not here, by putting you
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39290:4"/>to paynes, prevent the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which there you wil have to overtake them. The cauſe for which he ſuffered, is not ſpecified there at all; becauſe his ghoſtly Father was the penner of this Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and it became not him, who was the others Judge <hi>in foro Conſcientiae,</hi> to become his Accuſer, <hi>in foro Curiae.</hi> For, though his crimes were extant then, and are ſo ſtill upon <hi>Record;</hi> and that the Penitent did beſides (for his own greater confuſion, and the exaltation of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Patience, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Almighty God) give his Ghoſtly Father expreſs leave, to declare his ſins to the whole world; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet, would by no means
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39290:4"/>accept of that liberty; but ſpeaking onely, in general, words, of ſin at large; he<note n="(c)" place="margin">The inviolable ſeal of the Sacrament of Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and how ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a good Ghoſtly Father, is, and ought to be.</note> buries the particulars in profound ſilence, and under the ſeal of <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> for reverence of that holy <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,</hi> which muſt never upon any termes be defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>But I, who am free, will not conſent to have my hands tied up; but think it fit to let you know, that though his years were few, his crimes were great, and many; as ſtill appears up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Record</hi> of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</hi> And between the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, and eighteenth years of his age, (till the former of which times, his vigilant, and holy Mother, was able
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39290:5"/>to keep him in the diſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of piety, and vertue) h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſprouted out into great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitances; and, in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and at the head of the<note n="d" place="margin">Theſe are men who for murthers, and other extream inſolencies uſe to be baniſhed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. They were wont in <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly,</hi> to go in great troops up and down, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the paſſages.</note> 
               <hi>Banditi,</hi> he committed both Rapes and Murthers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with a moſt tempeſtuous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and tranſported mind. <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis inimica amicitia, ſeducti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis inveſtigabilis.</hi> He did too early caſt himſelf into the hands of flatterers, and wicked followers; and they made the way of ſin ſo ſmooth to him, that he could not hold from ſliding through it. Nor was his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der youth ſo innocent, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his education ſo excellent but that the moath, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of lewd company, did ſoon corrode it.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:39290:5"/>
            <p>Yet even herein was not his miſery ſo great, as the<note n="(f)" place="margin">It is proper to God alone, to draw good out of evil.</note> mercy of God, upon this occaſion was infinite. His crimes were not known, but by ſuch alone, as would not eaſily adventure to draw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves, the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſo great a Houſe as his, by detecting them. The manner only of his life, in reſpect of exceſſe, and riot, was ſuch, in the exterior, as wounded his noble and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mother to the very ſoul. The paſſages and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings whereof, are delivered in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> it ſelf, with ſo great tenderneſs, in the perſon of her ſon, as ſtrikes the heart of him that reads the words. I will not therefore touch that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39290:6"/>flowre, for fear of ſtriking off the dew, every drop whereof is a pearl. One cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance only, which is not mentioned there, I will here expreſs, becauſe it will not fail to ſerve, towards the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of compaſſion, in all their mindes, who read this ſtory.</p>
            <p>You<note n="(g)" place="margin">A cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the moving of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> ſhall therefore underſtand, that when the Mother had uſed all other poſsible endeavors, both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and humane, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, and reformation of her ſon, and all in vain (for ought ſhe was able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) ſhe cauſed him, for ſome offences (which yet, were far from being Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital) to be committed to Caſtle<note n="(k)" place="margin">This is the chief priſon in Rome, as the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> 
               <hi>S. Angelo,</hi> in hope
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39290:6"/>that ſuch a diſgrace, with the help of time, would make him return into him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. To this courſe ſhe was the more encourag'd, and in this hope the more confirmd becauſe by this reſtraint, he might be cut off from that all company, which was the very peſt, and poiſon of his ſoul. But ſee, and wonder at Gods providence.</p>
            <p>He<note n="(i)" place="margin">Any little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Publick diſgrace carries danger with it.</note> was no ſooner in priſon, but the fire of eager oppoſition brake forth of their hearts; whom, by his other more enormous inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, he had offended; for till then, it had been ſmoother'd under the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of that reſpect, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, which they carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards the Dignity, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39290:7"/>Nobility of his Houſe. But now <hi>publick Juſtice</hi> taking notice of his exceſſes, and <hi>Pope Clement</hi> the eight, in the beginning of his <hi>Pontificate,</hi> being deſirous to ſhew a ſtrong example, of what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial <hi>Juſtice</hi> the world was to expect at his hands; (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in repreſſing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhing that damnd crue of <hi>Banditi,</hi> who were ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to the ſtate of <hi>Italy,</hi> and of whom this young Lord was grown a leader) did ſuffer the Law to paſs on his perſon (for his Eſtate was not confiſcated, but went to his heirs, in blood). Being even yet therein, more <hi>juſt</hi> than <hi>Clement;</hi> though perhaps he would have been more <hi>Clement</hi> in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39290:7"/>pardoning than <hi>juſt</hi> in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, if he could, by way of anticipation, have ſeen the beauty and bravery of that noble ſpirit, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to live as long as a world can do, as a pattern of a mind moſt rarely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, between perfect Chriſtian piety, &amp; undanted incomparable magnanimity.</p>
            <p>But whilſt the<note n="(k)" place="margin">This Lady died in the year 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. and was buried on the 21. of Octob. in the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines Church at St. <hi>Andrea della valle;</hi> where ſhe erected ten M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes to be ſaid every day, for ever. She was of the houſe of the Dukes of <hi>Ceſi,</hi> and Siſter to the Marqueſs of <hi>Riano:</hi> Her name was <hi>la Signora Plaminia.</hi>
               </note> Mother and Son are both reſting now in peace and glory, as we may piouſly believe, I know not how, in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, to be ſilent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the powerful, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39290:8"/>wiſe, and infinitely good<note n="(l)" place="margin">The provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be deeply pondered, in this particular.</note> providence of Almighty God, towards both theſe ſervants of his. For, by the way of the<note n="(m)" place="margin">The Croſs is the high way to heaven.</note> 
               <hi>Croſs,</hi> he brought the ſon, in a few moments of time, to have a Soul in ſtate of great perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and he gave him, in the laſt hours of his life, that moſt happy kind of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> wherein he might not onely ſuffer, in ſatisfaction of the divine <hi>Juſtice,</hi> but paſs on by <hi>merits,</hi> (all grounded upon the mercy of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt our<note n="(n)" place="margin">No action of man is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious, but by the merits and firſt mercy of Jeſus Chriſt.</note> Lord (as all merits are) towards inſtant, and eternal felicity.</p>
            <p>And this he did, by as contrary means, as in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> he cured a certain <hi>Blind man,</hi> by<note n="(o)" place="margin">The omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of God, is not tied to means, but works his will, how he pleaſes.</note> 
               <hi>caſting dirt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39290:8"/>upon his eyes.</hi> For here he uſed the moſt indulgent tender care of the Mother, who loved that Son, as her own ſoul, towards the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that about, which was indeed, to make him happy in the end; but in the mean time, was the occaſion of his ſuddain, and reproachful death, whereby her very heart was to be broken. Taking him, ſo from her ſight, that thereby ſhe might enjoy a glorious ſight of him for ever; and dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ving her of all human comforts (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> (for as much as concerned her) were abridged, &amp; lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in him alone) that ſo ſhe might, with contempt of the world, ſend her whole heart up to heaven, whither
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39290:9"/>now her treaſure was gone before; and ſo be rewarded, for that tender and entire care, which ſhe had taken, for his pious education.</p>
            <p>It matters not much, what the blind, and dull world conceives, which placing Faith in fancy, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reaſon in the treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſenſe of fleſh &amp; blood, thinks all that to be miſery, which carries the face of pain, or ſhame, or any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty; and that true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs conſiſts in rowing for a while in ſome boat<note n="(q)" place="margin">A fit emblem to ſhew the vanity of wotldly pleaſure.</note> of muſick, down the tide; though it carry them ſoon after, where they are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ſplit upon rocks, or ſwallowed up by quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. Whereas God knows
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39290:9"/>(yea and men, who have his grace, are not ignorant) that a courſe of felicity not interrupted, or check'd by contrary winds, is a kind of fortune (for as much as concerns the next life) which in this deſerves ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pity, then envy; and that, ever ſince the death of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, the way of the <hi>Croſse,</hi> is<note n="[r]" place="margin">The Croſſe of Chriſt has made miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</note> not only the more ſafe, but even the more honourable; and that the pleaſures, and paſtimes of this life, are but a kind of butterfly for boys to play with, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt earthly felicity that ever was enjoy'd by man, if it died not as ſoon as it was born (which yet is the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary caſe of<note n="(s)" place="margin">World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſure ſpeaks fair but it lies.</note> worldly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39290:10"/>at leaſt, if it lived till it could learn to ſpeak, it told as many lies, as it uttered words; and charm'd them firſt, whom quickly after, it might lead towards a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice.</p>
            <p>How deſolate, would a worldling think, the caſe of <hi>Signor Troylo Savelli</hi> was, in that night when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the news of his ſo-inſtantly-approaching, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious death? And of that dear Mother of his, when ſhe heard the blow was given, which parted that head from thoſe ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? And<note n="(t)" place="margin">Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, made the Mother, and the Son, ſeem miſerable, and be happy.</note> yet with all, is it both well known, that the Mothers loſs of ſuch a ſon, did caſt her much more cloſe upon an union and ſole
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39290:10"/>dependence, for all her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, upon Almighty God, (wherein all the happineſs, we can have in this life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts) and it is morally cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the abundant grace of Contrition, and Charitie, which God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into the heart of the <hi>Son,</hi> even by the occaſion of his very ſins (ſo vaſtly and infinitely good is God) did put him inſtantly, after his death, into a ſtate ſo bleſſed, as that the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, under whom he died, &amp; thoſe <hi>Princes</hi> among whom he lived, and all the <hi>Monarchs</hi> of the whole world, may be accounted miſerable, according to their preſent ſtate, in reſpect of him. Our dear Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39290:11"/>eternally praiſed (and not onely by us, who know not how to do it well, but by all his holy Angels &amp; Saints) for his own infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſince he vouchſafes to<note n="(u)" place="margin">He could eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour himſelf o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny benefit to us, if he were ſo pleaſed.</note> place the point of his honour, in ſhewing mercies, and working wonders upon man ſo inſtantly, ſo ſweetly, ſo powerfully, and ſo like a God. And for having ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in his own ſacred ſoul, &amp; body, ſuch deſolations, and torments, as obtained, at the hands of the eternal Father, not only the remiſſion of our ſins, (if we will ſerve our ſelves of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and other remedies, he has left in the boſom of his holy <hi>Catholick Church</hi>) but the adorning alſo of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39290:11"/>our Souls with the inherent gifts, and graces of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. And yet further, for that he has known, how to make our very ſins, and grievous crimes themſelves, the means, ſometimes, whereby we obtain greater graces, then<note n="x" place="margin">This indeed is a mercy, which may well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the greatneſs of our God.</note> we ſhould have done, if we had not committed thoſe very ſins. Let the whole world there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adore thee, O Lord, and ſing praiſes to thee; and let all the powers of all ſouls cry out, and ſay with that holy King, and Prophet <hi>David, O Lord who is like to thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A great example, and proof of this power of God, and of the divinity of Chriſt our Lord, and the<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:39290:12"/>need of a great proportion of ſtupidity, to make him think, that, ſince God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf vouchſafed to be at the command of thoſe baſe and impure wretches, who too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> off his cloaths, and require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him to ſubmit himſelf t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe ſcourges, thoſe thorn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe nailes, thoſe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, for our ſakes, and ſins yet, on the other ſide, thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="b" place="margin">An ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> man, this proud rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worm, this crum o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> duſt, this drop of filth migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> keep, forſooth, a kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of State, and ſhould no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rather ſubmit himſelf (i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imitation of the humilit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only to ſuperiours, but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> equals, and even inferiour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo, and in fine to al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:39290:12"/>
               <note n="c" place="margin">This is the advice of S. Peter <hi>Subditi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtote omini creaturae.</hi>
               </note> the world when juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould be offer'd.</p>
            <p>The ſoul of this noble man, was ſo well ſoftned, and ſweetned by the unction of the Holy Ghoſt; as that neither the greatneſſe of his Nobility, nor the ardor of his youth, nor the natural boyling cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of his heart, nor the freſh memory of his proſperity, nor the unexpected arrival of his miſery, could make<note n="d" place="margin">A heart truely touched by Gods holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, wil o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome ſtrange difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> him once repine, or keep him from inſtantly abaſing himſelf. But falling deeply upon the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of his ſins; and weighing duly how ful of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merit he was, in the fight of God; and knowing exactly, that nothing is ſo truly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble, as a Soul which has forfeited his grace; and that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39290:13"/>
               <hi>rich,</hi> or <hi>poor,</hi> is little to the purpoſe; but<note n="e" place="margin">wherin eternal, true No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility conſiſts.</note> that the thing which imports, is to be, or not to be, the ſervant, or ſon of God; it is not ſtrange, to ſee him eaſt himſelf at the feet of common ſoldiers, and ſtretch out his hands, with ſuch meekneſſe, at the will of the meaneſt Jaylors, for the love of our Lord, to ſignifie thereby the deteſtation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he had himſelf, for having ſo preſumptuouſly offended that <hi>Eternal Majesty,</hi> which by all the Angels is adored.</p>
            <p>From<note n="f" place="margin">The reaſons why be was ſo frequent in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſins.</note> hence alſo did it proceed, that he ſo frequently confeſſed himſelf, in that laſt night of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s life; and could never think he had ſufficiently deplored his errors, and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the diſcorreſpondence,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39290:13"/>and ingratitude, wherewith he had anſwered the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable benefits of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. Wherein if any man ſhould think he uſed exceſſe, it will be much more lawful for me to doubt, that himſelf, either has a mean conceit of the <hi>Infinite Majeſtie</hi> which is offended, or an ignorant apprehenſion of the defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of all ſin which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; or a proud, and paltry miſtaking of the <hi>Nothing</hi> which man was, till he was created; and the worſe then <hi>Nothing,</hi> which afterward he grew, by ſinning. For<note n="g" place="margin">If you weigh theſe things well, you will change your wondring at him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring at your ſelf.</note> he that ponders theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, as he ought, and knowes, that the offences into which he falls are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39290:14"/>innumerable; and that the leaſt of them, which is committed againſt an <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite Majeſty,</hi> in reſpect of the object, is alſo infinite; and that, as no one good deed ſhall be unrewarded, by the rich Mercy of God, in Chriſt our Lord; ſo no one tranſgreſſion ſhall be left unpuniſhed, by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Juſtice, will eaſily beleeve that in the ſpace of a night, it is hard for one to be too curious, and too careful, in ſetting ſtraight the account of his whole life, under the piercing eye of Almighty God. But this <hi>Baron</hi> did, even by moments, in that ſhort time which was left, by the goodneſſe of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39290:14"/>quire new<note n="h" place="margin">Great light of God is wont to breed great love of him, &amp; great ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, for having ſo ſhame ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him.</note> light, and gain new love of our Lord, and new contempt, and deteſtation of himſelf; and, in the ſtrength thereof, found ſome actions to confeſs, which he had not conceived to be ſins before; and others, which he had confeſſed, he had done it with a ſorrow, far inferiour to that he then felt.</p>
            <p>For, abſtracting from the conſideration which he had of his ſins, againſt God (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect whereof, no ſoul is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently able to quake, and tremble under him) I truſt there is not a Readers eye in the world ſo dim, as not to diſcern his undaunted heart. And<note n="i" place="margin">The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted courage of this Baron.</note> that, no thought of death, had any power, to take the leaſt clarity from his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39290:15"/>the leaſt preſence from his memory; the leaſt agility from his wit; the leaſt order from his ſpeech; or ſo much as the leaſt <hi>puntillio</hi> from the civil reſpects and complements, which are uſed among perſons of his Nation, and Condition. Nor yet, on the other ſide, ſhall any man have reaſon to think, that the punctuality, which (through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the proceſſe of this <hi>Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) he ſhall find to have been obſerved by the <hi>Baron,</hi> in this laſt<note n="k" place="margin">This curteſie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement was not affected, but free and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</note> kind of courteſie, did proceed from the leaſt affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. Perhaps, if we look neer home, we may find ſome example to have been given of this, not long ago; but in the preſent caſe, no ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it can be entertain'd;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39290:15"/>both for many other reaſons, which will occur to him that reads the <hi>Relation;</hi> and becauſe (as I ſayd before) theſe exact tearms of Honor, and other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to the company, then preſent, are as it were natural to men of his country, and quality, and there would coſt them more pains to omit (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs their minds were put into diſorder, by ſome paſſion) then it would coſt others, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve where they were not ſo natural, as being learnt by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and Art. But yet, that in ſo ſad a caſe, this man, would, for good manners, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſet up his legs, or not ſo much, as ſtretch himſelf in the ſight of others, though his body did much incline him to it (according to that mention
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39290:16"/>which the <hi>Relation</hi> makes thereof) may well go for a great argument in him, of ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, of modeſty, and of magnanimity.</p>
            <p>And this is that which I thought fit to repreſent to you by way of <hi>Preface</hi> to this <hi>Story.</hi> You will find the traces and foot-ſteps of putting men to death, and the proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note n="l" place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral manners of treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents in ſeveral Countrys</note> Delinquents, to be very different, from that of our Country, both in relation to the body, and the ſoul. I take not upon me, to ſay which are better, &amp; which are worſe. With us, the <hi>Proceſſe</hi> of crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal perſons, is ever made, in the face of the world; but they are not ſufferd to have any Advocates who may defend their cauſes. In moſt other
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39290:16"/>Countrys, the Delinquents are permitted to have Advocates but the <hi>Proceſſe</hi> is made, though in publique Court, yet only in preſence of the Iudges and ſome few Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, and Officers. With us, the Delinquents are ſuffer'd to live ſom dayes after their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; which certainly is meant in compaſſion to them; in other parts, after they are judged to dy, and that it is ſo declared, they think they do men a greater curteſy, in putting them quickly out of pain. With us, there is no difference in the manner of death, between a Clown, and the beſt Gentleman of the Kingdom, under the degree of a <hi>Baron,</hi> unleſſe it be, in ſome very rare caſe, by moſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39290:17"/>particular favour of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> but in all other places, that I have ſeen, all Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are beheaded, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them from ſuch as are ignoble. With us, no indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is ever done to a <hi>Noble man</hi> of<note n="m" place="margin">ſuch as Barons are, and all above them.</note> 
               <hi>Title,</hi> by binding his hands, or arms, or the like; and that cuſtom I commend, as full of Honour; but in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other places, they bear no ſuch reſpect; in regard of the experience which they have found, and the fear, which ſtill they are in, of inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>But for as much, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the comfort of crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, in the preparation of their ſouls, towards the death of their bodyes, I cannot but note it, as a point of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39290:17"/>and piety moſt<note n="n" place="margin">It is the greateſt charity, to help men to dye well.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, that in very many of the good Towns of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spayn,</hi> there are certain <hi>Companies</hi> or <hi>Confraternities,</hi> of Gentlemen, well born and bred; who put this obligation of duty upon themſelves, to viſit the priſons, eſpecially in the night precedent to any execution. And, together with Religious perſons, and Ghoſtly Fathers, they watch, and pray, and exhort, and comfort the pooreſt crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Country, with the ſame induſtry, and charity, which is here afforded to this Noble man; And they all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them, to their death; and ſomtimes, diſcharge their dying hearts of care, either by undertaking to pay ſom of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39290:18"/>their debts, or by aſſiſting the poor wife, and children, which are left behind; or by obliging themſelves to get<note n="o" place="margin">S. <hi>Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> upon the point of her death, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> her Son to pray for her ſoul at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, when ſhe ſhould be dead: &amp; ſo he did. <hi>Vid. Conf. l.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Maſſes</hi> celebrated for their ſouls. And in conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of theſe good endeavours, we ſee men dy in thoſe parts, with another manner of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition towards God, than u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually they have with us; Where it is a lamentable thing, to ſee many of ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſtupidity, that, after lives moſt lewdly led, they go either drunk, or dancing to the Gallowes. As if, they were but to die in a Play; or as if, after this life, there were no immortality of the Soul; or elſe, at leaſt, no account to be rendred; I ſay not of idle words (which yet muſt be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39290:18"/>done, but of moſt wicked deeds, whereof many of them are guilty.</p>
            <p>The example we have here in hand, will yield, all the Readers of it in general, a good leſſon of Humilitie, Patience, Curteſie, Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, Obedience, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. And<note n="p" place="margin">All ſorts of people may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, by the good leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons here deliver'd.</note> it may ſerve for an inſtruction, not only to ſuch as die, by the hand of humane Juſtice; but to all thoſe alſo, who are to die by the hand of God, as we all ſhall be ſure enough to do. That ſo, we may the better take heed of ſin, which is to be ſo bitterly bewailed; and the more deeply we are fal'n into it, the more inſtantly we muſt implore the mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Almighty God; and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39290:19"/>diſpoſe our ſelvs to the doing of Penance; that ſo, by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, we may ſecure our ſouls from the danger of being plung'd into that lake of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pain. This leſſon I ſay, may reach to al Readers in general. But particular Readers may take out particular leſſons for themſelvs. The <hi>Mother</hi> wil ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh Mothers to be inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly careful for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; the <hi>Son</hi> will conjure chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from being inſolent, or diſobedient towards their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; and the<note n="q" place="margin">Theſe are they who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents in their death.</note> 
               <hi>Confortatori</hi> will exhort all men to ſhew charity to their diſtreſſed neighbors. And I beſeech our <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> to grant ſuch gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces both to them and me, as divine Majeſty knowes to be moſt needful for us,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:39290:19"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF THE CONVERSION and DEATH Of the Moſt ILLUSTRIOUS LORD SIGNOR <hi>TROILO SAVELLI,</hi> Who was beheaded in <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Caſtle <hi>Sant Angelo,</hi> on the 18. of <hi>April,</hi> 1592.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Writing the lives or deaths of others, if they be full of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary accidents, does uſually make the Readers wonder; if they be dolorous they cauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion; if proſperous, men grow
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39290:20"/>thereby into a deſire; if adverſe, into a fear. But this death, which now I am about to deliver, does-ſo imbrace the accidents of all theſe kinds; that whoever ſhall read it, as he ought, will<note n="(a)" place="margin">The power which this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, will have over ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all at once.</note> eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his mind to be filled at once, with all thoſe affections. And though, what I write, be, in fine, no more then a meer <hi>Relation</hi> of a Noble mans death, yet perhaps it may ſerve for a guide and example of men, through the whole courſe of their lives,</p>
            <p>I will nakedly therefore, declare the progreſſe, and period of this accident, as, in the night when it hapned, I went obſerving it pace by pace, to the comfort of mine own Soul. For<note n="(b)" place="margin">This <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> is purpoſely written in a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and plain manner.</note> here, all affectation, and ornament of ſpeech, would but prophane the majeſty of the thing; and no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor or ſtrife of wit, would ever arrive to the expreſſion of it. I will direct it only to thoſe, who, if perhaps they have not perſonal
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39290:20"/>and proper experience, of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable effects of Gods grace; at leaſt they will either have believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them of others, or read of them in good books, or heard them often delivered by Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. For, as to ſuch, who are meer ſtrangers thereunto, theſe things will ſeem incredible. Though even by ſuch, they may yet be thought the more probable, when at length they ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that at the inſtance of his excellent Mother, one of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers<note n="(c)" place="margin">Theſe are the good Prieſts of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by that great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God, <hi>B. Philip Neraeus.</hi>
               </note> of the <hi>Chieſa nova,</hi> had, with moſt diligent, and devout charitie, exerciſed <hi>his</hi> life, for the ſpace of a month, in ſpiritual things, whoſe converſion and death I have undertaken to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; and whatſoever effect it may have, more or leſſe, I will be ſure to write it for the benefit of ſouls, and upon no other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>It was then, upon the 17. of <hi>April</hi> at<note n="(d)" place="margin">This might be about ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of the clock at night, after our account.</note> four hours of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39290:21"/>night, of that Friday, when the news was brought to the Lord <hi>Troilo Savelli</hi> of his death, by an inferior Officer; Who coming to that chamber, where the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man was at his reſt, ſayd to him in this manner: <q>Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may be pleaſed to riſe and apparel your ſelf.</q> Whereunto he anſwer'd: <hi>This indeed is an hour, which has a little of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable; but yet whither wilt thou conduct me?</hi> The fellow told him, <hi>That place was to be made ready for new Priſoners;</hi> ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing this excuſe, that he might not fright him all at once. <hi>I beleeve</hi> (ſaies the young Lord) <hi>what thou haſt told me; but I confeſſe, thou madeſt me half a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid;</hi> and then, ſitting up in his bed, he ſaid, <hi>Let us apparel our ſelf, in the name of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having begun to put on his cloaths, as he was deſcending from his bed, <hi>Give mee leave,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for ſo long, as that I may
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39290:21"/>be ready.</hi> And ſo, caſting an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt countenance towards a little picture of our <hi>B. Lday,</hi> with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in her arms (which there he had of purpoſe) he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended himſelf in great earneſt to the mercy of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of his Mother, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he related to me. And the ſame night (ſome hour before the arrival of this news) he had raiſed himſelf out of his bed; and (kneeling down before that<note n="(e)" place="margin">He prayed before the Picture, but hee prayed to the B. Virgin to pray for him; and hee thought it no ill way to go by the M ther to the Son, as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp; Saints of Gods Church had done before him.</note> Picture) he ſayd, with abundant tears, <hi>O bleſſed and glorious Virgin, O that I might dy, if dy I muſt, with this very diſpoſition, which now I find in my heart.</hi> He told me, that the ſame night, when firſt he went to bed, he did, in a manner, aſſure himſelf his life would be ſaved; but that yet, more ſuddainly then he ever uſed, he roſe up, and could not hold from diſcharging his heart towards his dear Redeemer and the <hi>bleſſed Virgin.</hi> This was an ordinary uſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39290:22"/>of his, as afterward thoſe ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, under whoſe cuſtody he was, related to me; for they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten feigning not to ſee him, did many times perceave, that by ſtealth he caſt himſelf, upon his knees.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as he was apparail'd, the Officer returning, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, leſt (by reaſon of his freſh youth, being encountred with ſuch a terrible, and ſuddain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident) he might, through a kind of deſpairfull rage, either do hurt to himſelfe, or others, would needs, upon a ſuddain, caſt the manicles upon his hands; but gently ſtretching them out; <hi>My friend,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and humble reſigns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on.</note> ſaith he, <hi>behold, I am here ready to obey thy will, and the will of all the world, ſince the will of God is ſuch.</hi> Having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicled him, they lead him to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Chappel; when, at the iſſue out of his chamber, he bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <hi>He ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the ſign of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Croſſe.</hi> Ad omnem actum, ad omnem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ping<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Crutem. Hier. epiſt. ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtach. <hi>22.</hi> cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> himſelf, the beſt he could with the ſign of the holy <hi>Croſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:39290:22"/>with both his hands; and caſting up his eyes to Heaven, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly ſighed. For, ſeeing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, that there were more peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then might be needful for the changing of his Lodging, <hi>This,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is another manner of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then to change me only, from one place to another; but by the grace of God, I am ready for all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, ſilently going down to the Chappel, he was met by the<note n="(i)" place="margin">There are <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations</hi> of Gento in R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me (as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e are alſo in other great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly and Spain) who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelvs for the helping condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, to dy wel. The <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor</hi> &amp; <hi>Provedito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> are chief offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of theſe Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</note> 
               <hi>Governor,</hi> and the <hi>Proveditore,</hi> and by three others of them, who are called <hi>Confortatori della miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordia,</hi> in a faſhion, very ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the occaſion. Then one of them ſaid to him in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <q>My Lord, the hour which God has prefix'd for you, is even run out; render your ſelf into his merciful hands.</q> And he, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being troubled, otherwiſe, then by fetching a ſigh, (which yet was both ſoft and ſhort) did anſwer thus; <hi>Let God be bleſſed; behold I render my ſelf to him;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39290:23"/>and diſpoſe you of me.</hi> And ſo thoſe good and charitable Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that <hi>Congregation,</hi> with ſome Fathers of the <hi>Society of Jeſus,</hi> caſting themſelves round about him, and endeavouring to ſweeten the bitterneſſe of that news, by diſcreet and decent means, did comfort him the beſt they could. He yielded to all, and did even prevent them; and then, knocking his breaſt, and bowing down his head, and kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Crucifix,</hi> he demanded pardon, and like gentle wax, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd himſelf to be manag'd by them all.</p>
            <p>One of thoſe <hi>Confortatori,</hi> did, before all other things, put him in mind of making his <hi>Confeſſion.</hi> Upon the very firſt naming wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (recollecting himſelf) he ſaid, <hi>And</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">The firſt thing he did, was to confeſs himſelf.</note> 
               <hi>where is the Confeſſor?</hi> And they ſhewing him a Prieſt of their Company, with his <hi>Albe</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Theſe are ſome of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdot al veſtments which are uſed in celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</note> upon his back, and his <hi>Stole</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his neck, (that afterward
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:39290:23"/>he might ſay Maſſe, in the proper time) the firſt thing he did, was to be confeſſed; and we all went out, to leave the place free to them.</p>
            <p>He being confeſſed, and we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, we began to diſpoſe him towards a good end, by divers ſpiritual exerciſes, fit for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And after many had ſpoken, I alſo began thus to ſay; <q>
                  <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> This is that paſſage, which whoever does once make well, acquires eternal felicitie; and if once it be ill made, it draws after it everlaſting miſery. It now imports your Lordſhip to make it well, that you may eſcape that eternity of torment. This paſſage is narrow, uneven, hard, and full of ſtones, and thorns; all the world ſees it, and your Lordſhip finds it by experience; but<note n="(m)" place="margin">Our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, doth even the uneven way of death.</note> behold ſweet <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who, by his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, will even it all. Caſt your ſelf, my Lord, upon him;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39290:24"/>and then you, will be able to ſay with courage, <hi>Omnia</hi>
                  <note n="(n)" place="margin">I can do all things in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts me.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, in co qui me comfortat.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>He anſwerd thus, with a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and even ſmiling countenance, <hi>Omnia poſſum in eo qui me comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. By the mercy of my deer</hi> Jeſus, <hi>I know the neceſſity of making this paſſage well; I acknowledge his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence over me, and to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence I add, that of his love. For as much as with extraordinary love it is, that he has brought me hither. I ſee it, I confeſſe it. And how often, dear Father, have I been, as I may ſay, in the very jaws of death; which, if at that time it had ſeized me, infallibly this ſoul, and body of mine had periſhed. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, with great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacrity.</note> 
               <hi>the cunning of my Chriſt to ſave me, he has made choyce of this way.</hi> And then bowing, and baring his head, and, with great life of ſpirit, raiſing himſelf from his chair, he further added; <hi>I accept of this election which God has made;</hi> and then caſting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:39290:24"/>upon his knees, before the <hi>Alter, Nay I thank thee</hi> (ſays he) <hi>O my good Father, for thy ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and loving care of me; who have not only been a wandring, but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious Son of thyne. To thee it belongs, to ſmooth and even the ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godneſs of this way; ſince thou haſt been pleaſed to addreſſe me by it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo, bowing his face even almoſt down to the ground, he remayn'd a while, in mental Prayer.</p>
            <p>Being therefore wiſhed to ſit down, he was ſcarce ſetled in that poſture, when turning towards me, he ſayd thus, in mine ear: <hi>You, whom, through my good fortune, I have heere, to help me, in this ſo weighty and high affayr, in the place of God do you command mee. I</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e gives himſelf away to his Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> 
               <hi>give my ſelf, as bound into your hands. The Prince has diſpoſed of my body; do you as much with my ſoul.</hi> I ſayd therefore to him: I firſt deſire, my Lord, that you make the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">This is a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s faith with an entier ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the good will of God.</note> which is wont to be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39290:25"/>delivered by ſuch as are going to God. Which being publikly pronounced by him, with great ſence and ſpirit, (he taking up and repeating my words) I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him further thus: <q>You ſhall now make all thoſe acts of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, which I ſhall call to your mind; having the eyes thereof, firſt bent upon God, being offended, as a <hi>Creator,</hi> as a <hi>Preſerver,</hi> as a <hi>Iuſtifier,</hi> and as a <hi>Glorifier.</hi> Next, upon you ſelf, who have offended him; being his creature, his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould ſervant, his Chriſtian ſlave; and one ſo deeply obliged, by this benefits. Thirdly, upon the offences them ſelves which you have committed; and be ſory at your hart, for having committed them; and<note n="(r)" place="margin">For who can ever call to mind all his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſins</note> if not in particular for them all, at leaſt for the<note n="(s)" place="margin">He had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready confeſſed his ſinns; and now he is but exhorted to renew his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for them.</note> moſt greivous of them, which ſhall repreſent themſelves to your memory. Fourthly, upon the good you
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:39290:25"/>have omitted; and the time you have loſt; and the yeares you have miſpent. Fifthly, upon the ſcandal you have given. And if any thing more be to be done, if<note n="(t)" place="margin">We cannot be ſaved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe firſt we make reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well of fame, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f goods, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> to make reſtitution, either of fame, or goods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if to pardon others, or to ask pardon your ſelf; reſtore and pardon, and ask pardon. If to perform any vows, or fulfil any promiſes; perform and fulfil them. Or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, if you leave any debts, or if you will make any ſignification of your repentance, and pious end, you are now to put your hand to work.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe things he offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt readity, and did exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them all with ſo great devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry one now began to change his ſtile in ſpeaking to him; For finding, that whereas before they thought they ſhould have to do but with a young man, or rather a youth, and weakling,<note n="(u)" place="margin">He infinitely overcame their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.</note> they were now to treat with a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39290:26"/>manly, generous, and ripe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, far ſuperior to that, which might peradventure have been expected of him; One of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortatori</hi> began, with great diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to diſcourſe upon the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of Death, which our moſt ſweet <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> did, by his ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, diſpoſſeſſe of bitterneſſe. <q>Confi e, ſaith he, and caſt your thoughts upon him, and ſay, <hi>Pone</hi>
                  <note n="(x)" place="margin">Place me, O Lord, nearthee, and let the hand of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fight againſt me.</note> 
                  <hi>me Domine juxtate, &amp; cujuſvis manus pugnet contrame.</hi> And if now you find any bitter taſte in death, during this ſhort night, as without fail you will, ſay,<note n="(y)" place="margin">O my Father, not as I will, but as thou wilt, thy will be done.</note> 
                  <hi>Pater mi, non ſicut ego volo, ſed ſicut tu, fiat voluntas tua.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The contrite Lord made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thus, <hi>the wickedneſſe of my life frights me, more, than the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of my death. Oh how wretchedly have I ſpent theſe eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein years? How ill have I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood my Saviour? How ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful have I been for his noble favors?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39290:26"/>How rebelliouſly have I lived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his laws? And how have I run like a wild, unbridled horſe, in theſe later years of mine, without any manner of reſtraint, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the preſent occaſions, or conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, or</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">The ſinner, is only to blame himſelf for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> 
               <hi>rather (for I have ſaid ill) whereſoever mine own paſſions, and blind affections had a mind to plunge me? It is I, and none but I, who did precipitate my ſelf; and yet you bid me ſix my thoughts, and hopes upon God; and ſay,</hi> Pone me, Domine, juxta te, &amp; cujuſvis manus pugnet contra me, fiat voluntas tua.</p>
            <p>Upon this, another of the <hi>Confortatori</hi> proceeded thus: <q>It is an act of magnanimity, not to fear the angry face of death; and of humility, to acknowledg our offences; but of confidence to hope for pardon, as your Lordſhip doth; who well may ſay, <hi>Propter nomen tuum Domine, propitiaberis peccato meo, multum eſt enim.</hi>
               </q> For thy names ſake, O
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39290:27"/>Lord, thou ſhalt forgive my ſin, for it is great. <hi>O how great,</hi> ſaid <hi>Signor Troilo? Even as great, after a manner, as is the mercy of God, which is immenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Proveditore</hi> then ſayd; <q>Your Lordſhip, may, if you be ſo pleaſed, make your laſt <hi>Will,</hi> and <hi>Teſtament;</hi> to the end no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thought may ſollitcie you, but that of your ſoul.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon the <hi>Baron,</hi> without the leaſt delay, by way of anſwer, bade them write. And, having taken out of his pocket, a little note, which he carryed about him, he ſuddenly dictated his <hi>Teſtament;</hi> wherein he deliver'd ſome particulars, in my opinion, very conſiderable. Firſt,<note n="(a)" place="margin">The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations which may be made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the manner of pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Will.</note> of tender Devotion; for he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his ſoul to God, by moſt dear and religious words. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of Ripeneſſe, which was more than of a young man; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, in a moſt particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, he had remembrance of all
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39290:27"/>his ſervants. Thirdly, of a moſt lively Contrition; becauſe, with a moſt Profound, internal affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mind, he demanded pardon of many, even by name. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of great Magnanimity; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he conjured the Lady his Mother, that ſhee would pardon all his adverſaryes, as he himſelf did pardon them a thouſand times over. Beſeeching<note n="(b)" place="margin">what a true, and noble Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an heart was this?</note> her, by a long, and chriſtian circuit of words, that ſhee would never reſent his death; but hee laid the fault upon himſelf, in all things.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, of Religious Piety; leaving large almes to many Churches, and other holy places; accommodating many poor<note n="(c)" place="margin">This is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, much u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly.</note> Virgins, with dowryes, at the particular diſcretion, and to be perform'd by the care of his heirs; that God might the rather have mercy on him. Sixtly, of entire Iuſtice; becauſe hee took care, that even more then was due by him, ſhould be reſtored.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39290:28"/>Seaventhly, of noble Gratitude; becauſe hee rewarded whoſoever had don him any ſervice in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Eighthly, of affectionate Reverence; becauſe hee did in a moſt ſweet, and dear manner, ask pardon of the Lady his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the reſt of his kinred, beſides the expreſſing of other complements.</p>
            <p>Having ended his laſt <hi>Will, Well Sirs</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>behold we have this reſidue of time, now wholly free, for the care of our ſoul.</hi> And turning towards me, ſaid, <hi>It</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">He ſpeaks of his ſoul, for as much as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the guiding of it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God.</note> 
               <hi>is in your hand, and therefore diſpoſe of it; for this only is now in my power to give you.</hi> I then, by way of anſwer, ſaid, Give your ſelf, my Lord, to <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>I do ſo,</hi> ſaid he; and he ſaid it inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And I again, Give your ſelf wholly to him. He ſaid, <hi>I do.</hi> Conſecrate your ſelf; he ſtill ſaid, <hi>I do.</hi>
               </q> Make your ſelf, ſaid I, entirely his. <hi>But how</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>O Father, ſhall I make my ſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:39290:28"/>his, if I be unworthy, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps his</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">As all grievous ſinners are, if they do not through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent, which no man can be ſure he hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently done, though he may have great hope of it.</note> 
               <hi>enemy?</hi> But in the mean time, whilſt the <hi>Will</hi> was writing, he that wrote it put us in mind, it was to be publickly read; that ſo it might be cloſed up with a due<note n="(f)" place="margin">A Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam nt is not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid there, if it have not ſeven witneſſes at leaſt.</note> number of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. And whilſt this was in doing, that is, whilſt the <hi>Notary</hi> was reading it; three things of ſome conſideration did occur. The firſt, that when he read how he recommended his ſoul to God, <hi>My body,</hi> ſays he, (drawing near me, according to his cuſtom) <hi>I diſpoſe not of; for now, it is no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er mine. It once was mine, and I would it had not been ſo; but</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">He acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and juſtice of God in all things.</note> 
               <hi>it is more than reaſon, that I, having had ſo great care of it, in my life time, for my puniſhment, ſhould not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, to have any power over it, now in my death. Let them therefore do with it what they will; for I ſacrifice it to God whatſoever it is. Father,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39290:29"/>will not ſuch an O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lation as this do me good?</hi> It will, ſaid I, without doubt it will: and what<note n="(h)" place="margin">For he that gives his body, ſhews in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, that he has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his ſoul.</note> more acceptable oblation can be made to our Lord, than that of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? The ſecond, That when the <hi>Legacies</hi> were read, it being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, by the manner of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing one of them, that he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd himſelf as faulty, in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thing, wherein indeed he was not ſo; and therefore the <hi>Will</hi> was to be redreſſed, as I deſired, which ſerved not only, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) for ſecuring his conſcience, but for the ſaving alſo of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Upon this, putting off his <hi>Montiera,</hi> or cap, <hi>O Father,</hi> ſaith he, (and he did it half ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) <hi>are you now taking care of my reputation, and of the</hi> puntillios <hi>of Honour, and of that ſmoak or vanity of the world? Let my ſoul be ſaved, and let all the vain Honour periſh, which I either had, or might have had. Do you not remember that which even</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">This is not mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here before; For he ſaid many other things which are not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this ſhort <hi>Relation.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>now you ſaid,</hi> Mihi mundus
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39290:29"/>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">The world is crucified to me, and I to it.</note> crucifixus eſt, &amp; ego mundo. <hi>In a word, let not the Soul be touched, but let my Honor be blaſted, according to that accoumpt, which the blind world is wont to make of Honour; that it may ſerve as a part of the puniſhment, which is due to me.</hi> The Third, that at the ſame inſtant, his hat was brought him; and one of his people, being deſirous to take his <hi>Montiera</hi> from off his head, <hi>what are you doing</hi> ſaith he? They anſwerd, they would give him his hat. But he bad them let it alone, ſaying, <hi>it imported not;</hi> and he added, with a ſoft voyce, <hi>Look here a while, they would fain honor this head of mine, which I am to loſe, within few hours, for my ſinns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Will</hi> being then read, and cloſed up, he threw himſelf, as it were upon me, with a moſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt kind of ſweetnes, and ſaid, <hi>Father I am already reconciled; but I would fain make a general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of my whole life, to your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:39290:30"/>And though, ſince I came into priſon, I did the ſame, in effect, at the inſtance of my Lady-Mother; yet know, I had then no light, or fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of my ſinns, in reſpect of that, I now diſcover in my heart. It being One thing, dear Father, for a man to confeſſe himſelf, when be is in the ſight of death; and another, to do it not thinking of death; or at leaſt but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering it, as afar off.</hi> And ſo, call<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing for a<note n="(l)" place="margin">There are litle bookes, of add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſe, whereby men are taught how to confeſſe their ſins exactly.</note> little book, which he had obove in the priſon, ſhewing the way, how to confeſſe ones ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly well (which his good MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER had brought him ſom dayes before) he began his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion;</hi> Wherein, my Lord God knowes, that, as it is lawful for me, by that ample authority, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf gave me, to declare as much thereof, as I ſhould think fit; ſo if I were able to expreſſe it, I ſay not, that <hi>Rome</hi> would be aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at it, but all <hi>Italy</hi> would be ſo. For if I ſpeak of the exact manner he held; for as much as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39290:30"/>concern'd the particular deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding even to idle words, and any other<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> is no ſuch curſory or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial thing, as they who know it not, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and ſay.</note> ſuch peccadillo, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought I was hearing ſom well exercis'd Religious man. In the explicating of circumſtances, and the unfolding of intricate and intangled caſes, it was, as if he had been ſome profound Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine. In relating the determinate number, and the various kinds of his ſins, he made proof of one, who had a moſt freſh, and happy memory.</p>
            <p>This rare Gentleman, pawſing now and then, between the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his ſins; and ſuffering certain tears to fall quietly upon my knees, would be wiping them away: and that being don, he would often ſay with ſighs, <hi>O Father, how</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">He had great reaſon to ſay ſo.</note> 
               <hi>good has our Lord been to me? Let him now be bleſſed, as often, and yet more often, than I have offended him, in my former life.</hi> Whilſt he was accuſing himſelf of his faults, he would expreſs them
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39290:31"/>in certain few, but thoſe all live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and moſt pious words; and in ſom particular eaſes, ſo dearly tender, that in his countenance, one might ſee evident ſigns how his very heart was even rent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. So that between<note n="(o)" place="margin">He pawſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, both to reſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to recall his ſins, more freſhly to his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; for though it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was all but one <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,</hi> till <hi>Abſolution</hi> was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> the times of his <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> the <hi>Confortatori</hi> (doubting left perhaps he might incline to faint) would be asking him, if he needed not ſomwhat to reſtore, and comfort himſelf. To which he anſwer'd, (ſpeaking pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, and more than once to me) <hi>This</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">An admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion.</note> 
               <hi>only comfort, or reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive I would deſire, That my very heart might burſt for grief, and ſatisfaction might ſo be</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">To the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of God; his ſorrow being dignified by the death and paſſion of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord.</note> 
               <hi>given, for my ſins, if perhaps even that, would ſerve the turn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as, to my think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he did melt as it were, by ſo enlarging himſelf in his <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> I had an eye upon him, and I ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39290:31"/>to ſay thus to him. <q>My dear <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> be not ſo exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively curious, and particular, in accuſing your ſelf; eſpecially of thoſe your former ſins, whichly not now upon your ſoul.</q> 
               <hi>O</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">See how tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this heart was touched with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for his ſins, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelf.</note> 
               <hi>Father</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I have waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my whole life, in offending God; and will you have me, or ſhall I content my ſelf, in one ſingle hour, to demand pardon for ſo many offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? So long in ſinning, and ſo ſhort in confeſſing my ſins? That I am troubleſom to you, my dear Father, I well diſcover; but how can I help it, if I be forc'd to it?</hi> And here again, he began to make for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, a very bath of tears. And, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting what I had ſaid, after his own conceit, he added, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ears redoubled, <hi>And this alſo do my ſins deſerve, by way of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that, having cast ſo much, ſo very much time away, in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of my ſalvation, I ſhould now want time, wherein I might even confeſſe my ſins. Pardon me, dear
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39290:32"/>Father, and endu e this trouble, for the love of God; for you ſhall</hi>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">To do a good work by the grace, and for the love of God, is meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; for ſo Chriſt our Lord hath made it.</note> 
               <hi>merit, in his ſight, by helping this poor ſoul of mine, towards ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and I will remain with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to you, when I ſhall go by the mercy of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and your good meanes, into the place of reſt.</hi> And finding that his teares ſtill increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I confeſſe my weakneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was ſuch, that I could not contain my ſelf from expreſſing alſo a tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by tears.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as he perceiv'd this, he ſaid; <hi>Father, your Reverence weeps, yet you weep not for your ſelf, but for me; and yet you will not have me weep for my ſelf.</hi> But then, both of us being ſilent for a time, he after, began again to confeſſe, with thoſe accuſtomed ſhort words, but full of ſubſtance, and propriety; making me write down all thoſe things he confided to me, for the diſcharge of his conſcience. Whilſt I was writing, he would needs for his content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39290:32"/>hold the Standiſh, in his own hands, and read thoſe lines, when I had done, and kiſſe them, and then bath them in tears.</p>
            <p>But of nothing did he accuſe himſelf ſo much, as of all that, which had any relation to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, his Mother. Nor am I able by any means to expreſſe, with what abundance of tears he accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied thoſe accuſations of himſelf. For, beginning even from his very Infancy, <hi>Father,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">A large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able grief he had, for his diſodedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the Lady his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> 
               <hi>have committed many offences againſt God, yet at this time, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, I am not ſo much afflicted for any thing, as for not having known, how to ſerve my ſelf of that tender love, and prudence, and patience, which my Lady Mother expreſſed, in the education of me. For even when I was yet a child, ſhe gave me in charge to certain learned and religious Preceptors; who till I arrived to have ſixteen years of age, did with great fidelity, and ſufficiency, teach me, not only
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39290:33"/>the literature of</hi> Humanity, <hi>but</hi> Philoſophy <hi>alſo. And they further ſhewed how</hi> I <hi>was to addreſs my ſelf to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards piety, by their good example, and advice. Nor yet content with this; how ſollicitous was ſhe alſo, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure by many other means, that I might proceed, both in</hi> Learning, <hi>and</hi> Vertu? <hi>For</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">See here the Image of a holy and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> 
               <hi>concerning that of</hi> Learning, <hi>ſhe gave me store of books, of time, of oportunity, and a thouſand tender favours, which were convenient for thoſe years of mine. And for the inducing mee to</hi> Vertu, <hi>ſhe addreſſed me to choice of good Converſations, ſpiritual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, excellent Sermons, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who might from time to time give me counſail. Commanding, and cauſing me to be lead to</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; <hi>not only upon all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Feasts of the year, but once alſo every moneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And, till this very time, when I am ſpeaking to your Reverence, you may (if you will take the payns) find, among my papers, moſt evident testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39290:33"/>of what I am now ſaying; and eſpecially</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Note her dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences for the pious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of her ſon.</note> 
               <hi>a ſhort manner of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, how to ſpend the whole day well. The things beſides whereof ſhee did admoniſh me, were, in a manner, infinite. When I was yet a little one, ſhee kept mee in awe, by threats, yea and by ſtroaks ſometimes; and when I was grown elder, ſhe endeavourd to do it, by the fair means of requeſts and promiſes; and oftentimes, with ſo many tears, as that now, they are as many lances to paſſe through my my heart. She likewiſe procured that</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bleſſed Philippo Neri,</hi> was his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, at Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. The <hi>Chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Nuova</hi> was a new Church, then and now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> whence they are called O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atorians.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed man</hi> Philippo, <hi>of the</hi> Chieſa nuova <hi>to aſſiſt, &amp; bold me, when I was</hi> confirm'd; <hi>and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward I ſhould make particurar friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She kept me far off from looking upon ill examples; and held me neer her ſelf, after the manner, as I may ſay, of a Religious life; exhorting me often day and night that I would live Nobly,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">True Chriſtianity, is true Nobilily.</note> 
               <hi>and like a Chriſtian. Nor did that bleſſed mouth of hers, ever
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39290:34"/>ceaſe to ſay,</hi> Troilo, my Son, fear God, and love God. <hi>To this end ſhe took upon her, the government of all my</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caſtello</hi> in Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies both the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion houſe, and the Town, or vilage belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it.</note> Caſtles; <hi>and the care of all my affairs; living in a continual ſtate of, between hope and fear of the proof I ſhould make. Nor was there a</hi> Religious Houſe, <hi>or</hi> Monaſtery, <hi>to the prayers whereof, ſhe recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me not. Nor came there any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons to her, nor did ſhe meet with any abroad, to whom, all forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of her ſelf, ſhe would not ſay,</hi> Pray<note n="(b)" place="margin">Som body prayed ſo well for him, as to make him a Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</note> for my Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I, ungrateful to her ſo great benefits, when I grew to have ſixteen years of age, did render her ſo ill pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for ſuch a huge ſum of love; as that I even parted houſe with her, &amp; did outrage her, both by words and deeds; in ſuch ſort, as that the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of all puniſhment, ſeems a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times leſſe to me, then my deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And when, dear Father, I think upon the tears ſhe was ever ſheading for me both by day, and in thoſe nights, ſo ſadly ſpent, and on the ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39290:34"/>ſhe ſufferd upon my occaſion, I find contentment, in that I am to dy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, me thinks, I may, in part, over-ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow ſo many of my lewd behaviours,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible love of this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to her Son.</note> 
               <hi>yet, after I had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated my ſelf from her, did ſhe give over to ſollicite me with notes, and letters, and meſſages, and a thouſand other inuentions, that I would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to retire my ſelf from vitious converſations; and ſhe would p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y me, &amp; importune me, and coniure me, that I would take to good. And well I know, that no kind of devotion was omitted by her, for my reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by viſiting both as many</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>and</hi> Religious perſons, <hi>as ſhe knew in Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In fine, ſhe came often to me, both by day and night, whilſt I was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering up and down in ſuch company: and</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">It ſeems<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to have been a kind of ſtrife and war; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween how kind, a Mother could tel how to be, and how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind a Son.</note> 
               <hi>when ſhe found me out, ſhe would caſt her ſelf, even at my feet, that ſo I might once be drawn to open mine eys, and conſider the precipice I was approaching; and the ruines beſides the Shame, that would ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39290:35"/>come upon me; and that I would return to Chriſt; and once truly weigh (for theſe were her ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words)</hi> whoſe Son I was; <hi>and that I would conſider, what thing that was, which had ever been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me, whereby in that deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate faſhion, I ſhould abandon all care of my Eſtate, Life, and Honour. And uſually ſhe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied theſe admonitions, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of hers, with moſt tender tears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Somtimes again, ſhe would turn aſide, and, caſting up her eyes to God, beſeech him, either to convert me, or elſe</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Her prayer was heard in a better though in another manner then ſhe moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</note> 
               <hi>to take me to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And this I can ſay with all truth, that from the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to this inſtant, wherein now I l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve, ſhe has never ceaſed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour my ſalvation. For even from the firſt time ſhe</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">She was in Rome at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment, but when ſhe ſaw how the World would go with him ſheretired thence, with her load of ſorrow.</note> 
               <hi>came to ſee me here in priſon, ſhe exhorted me to</hi> Confeſſion, <hi>and ever ſince, ſhe has come, as thick as hail upon me, ſomtimes with Religious men,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39290:35"/>and ſomtimes with pious Books. So long, as that now at laſt, I am, by the favor of God, returnd a little into my ſelf. And, beſides the cutting off all occaſions of doing ill, ſhe gave me many great oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of good, with fervent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, that I would reſtore my ſelf, to the ſervice of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor could ever any Son deſire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny favor, or contentment of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which mine did not, of her ſelf, impart to me. And I, on the other ſide, have ſerved, but to make her life most unfortunate, by this period of mine. I beſeech our Lord forgive me, and to receive the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture affliction of her heart, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſcount of my offences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then towards the end of his Confeſſion; <hi>I deſire</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>a favour of you now, dear Father, which you muſt not deny me. It is, that I may have liberty to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment my ſins with tears; and that, by them, I may give teſtimony to the Divine Majeſty, of the</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:39290:36"/>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">That ſo the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent himſelf by find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, might have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of comfort</note> 
               <hi>grief, wherewith my heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds within.</hi> Weep out, ſaid I, ſince our Lord gives you ſuch a deſire of weeping.</p>
            <p>I had ſcarce brought forth this laſt word, when already, there began to fall a moſt abundant ſhowre of tears from his eyes; in ſuch ſort,<note n="(h)" place="margin">An admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and almoſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition.</note> as that he bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a good part of one of my arms; and my ſleeve was as wet through, as if it had rained from above. Which accident I obſerving, after ſome half quarter of an hour, and doubting, leſt his heart might ſo diſcharge it ſelf by his eyes, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the apprehenſion he might have of death, then other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; <q>I deſired, that, for the love of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> he would quiet himſelf, and not multiply his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, nor continue to torment his mind, in that manner.</q> To this he anſwer'd; <hi>Father, I give you my faith, that I do not, at all, bewail my death; but I do only, and purely, lament the offences I have
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39290:36"/>committed againſt Almighty God. And</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">A happy conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Chriſtian ſorrow, with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſo much hope in the mercy of my dear Lord, that not only I ſhall ſhed no tears for my death, but not ſo much as change my countenance. Father, I bewail my moſt unfortunate life, and not my moſt happy death. That life was, indeed, moſt unfortunate; whereas this death is moſt happy; for in fine, if in that, I lived an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to God, I hope, in this, I ſhall dy his friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Well then, ſaid I, proceed in your Confeſſion, that ſo you may dy the friend of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and lay a part of your tears aſide the while.</q> Whereupon, the moſt obedient young Gentleman, accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelf to my direction, did proceed juſt where he had left.</p>
            <p>At this I wondred ſo much the more; for as much as I my ſelf had forgotten it, though I alſo had one of thoſe little Books in my hand, which inſtruct how a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> may be well made.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39290:37"/>But he, going on, layd before me, (as if it had been in one ſingle proſpect) the whole courſe of his life, with ſo great clarity, and brevity, that I found my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to ask him, if during many daies before, he had not applyed himſelf to make ſuch a preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. To which the young Noble man made this very anſwer: <hi>So great is the light (as I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy inſinuated) which my dear</hi> Lord Jeſus <hi>vouchſafes at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to give me, of my whole life, that even whilſt I am confeſſing, me thinks I behold all my actions</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">This was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Almighty God.</note> 
               <hi>as in a glaſſe; and I read all my thoughts and words, as in a Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, without doubt, ſo it was. For he, without ever miſtaking a word, did ſo call all his ſins to mind, that by that time he want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed little of having declared them all diſtinctly. Only at the very end, as it were, of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, he return'd to repeat ſome things which he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39290:37"/>ſaid; and I doubting that he did ſo, as having forgotten what he had expreſſed before, I told him of that inadvertence (as I reputed it) when yet he made me this anſwer: <hi>I know well, dear Father, that I repeat ſome things; but I do it, to the end I may now more perfectly deteſt them, and be confounded in my ſelf. And eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">How deſirous this Soul was, to make God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends.</note> 
               <hi>ſince I have paſſed the greateſt part of my life in ſuch things as theſe, to the diſpleaſure of our Lord, I do now for the better pleaſing of him, paſſe this time of my death, in a miſliking remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of them. And if it be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome to your Reverence, as I know it is, ſo often to hear my ſo many offences; do you remember once for all, that this is the Soul of a ſinner, for whom Chriſt dyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Nay, ſaid I, if your Lordſhip, have any ſuch apprehenſion, you may repeat as much, and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as you pleaſe; for I only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed you of it before, as think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39290:38"/>perhaps you might have don it by errour.</q> 
               <hi>The errour</hi> (ſays he) <hi>was m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, and a grievous error it was to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffend thoſe ſo many waies, who did ever ſtand in my d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fence. But however that be, in this reſpect as in ſome others, I ſhall dy content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in that I can never ſatisfie my ſelf, with confeſſing my faults to you, dear Father; Which now, by the goodneſſe of God, are as well known by me, as heretofore they were little eſteem'd; and are now as bitterly lamented, as heretofore they gave me guſt, though it were a falſe one. I</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">The man did even melt between grief and love.</note> 
               <hi>wiſh, (O thou moſt ſweet Saviour of my Soul) I had, as well, a thouſand tongues, that ſo I might fully cenfeſſe them; a a thouſand eyes, that ſo, I might bitterly bewail them; and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand hearts, that ſo, eternally I migh deteſt them. And that this grief for my ſins, committed againſt God, might ſo break my heart; as the inſtrument of Juſtice, will take my head, for thoſe I have committed concerning men.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:39290:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I do, good Father, (by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God) know what a ſinner I am. As a ſinner, I lament my ſelf, and as a ſinner I will dy, but a ſinner, all humbled and contrite; and with my tears I will make my Funerals; then ſuffer me to perform them, after mine own faſhion.</hi> And here even I, not<note n="(n)" place="margin">I cannot blame him.</note> being able to contain my ſelf from weeping, was obſerv'd by him, who ſaid thus. <hi>Moſt happy Funerals are therefore theſe of mine, which are ſolemnized by the ſervants of God. Yet this part belongs not to you, but only as being a Father to my Soul. Who knows, but that by theſe mutual tears, and this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of tenderneſſe, my impure conſcience may indeed be cleanſed?</hi> Thus both of us, being ſilent for a while, he then proceeded: <hi>Well, my good Father, it is now high time that by the</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">This authority was given to his true Church by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and in his name, &amp; by his power, 'tis exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</note> 
               <hi>Authority, which God has given you,</hi> to looſe, and bind men <hi>on earth, you looſe me, from ſo many chains of ſin, which
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39290:39"/>hang upon me. To the end that, as you have taught me, I may ſay,</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditui meo dabis gaudium &amp; laetitiam, &amp; exultabunt oſſa humiliata. <hi>And firſt I beſceech you you give me</hi> Abſolution, <hi>and then, I may perform my</hi> Penance. <hi>Though indeed what</hi> Penance, <hi>carrying pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion to my ſinns, is your</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence <hi>able to impoſe?</hi> At this, he caſt himſelf at my feet, and bowed his head to my knee, where I had laid my left hand; and he all bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with tears, and kiſſed it, and expected the <hi>Penance</hi> &amp; <hi>Abſolution,</hi> Which I gave him, fully, in form of a<note n="p" place="margin">This is a ful remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances requir'd by the ancient diſcipline of the Church.</note> 
               <hi>Plenary Iubiley,</hi> according to the moſt ample priviledge,<note n="(q)" place="margin">By the Popes.</note> granted to thoſe of the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the<note n="(r)" place="margin">It is called a congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of <hi>M ſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo great a wo k of charity and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they imploy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note> 
               <hi>Miſericordia.</hi> Being abſolv'd, and having don his <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> with incredible affection of mind, he ſate down again by my direction; and then, the reſt cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and encircled him after the accuſtomed manner.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:39290:39"/>
            <p>I then ſpake firſt to him after this ſort: <q>Moſt Illuſtrious Lord <hi>Troilo,</hi> our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt</hi> whom here we have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, did, by dying upon the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> give remedy, in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, this night to three things, among many others. He<note n="(s)" place="margin">An applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll of life and comfort.</note> dyed in the flower and vigour of his youth; that your Lordſhip might not have too much indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and compaſſion of your own tender youth, and ſo might ſay, <hi>O, but why is my life taken away in ſo tender years?</hi> And this is the firſt. He dyed, and he dyed of a violent death; that to your Lordſhip it might not ſeem inſupportable, to dy upon neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and ſo you might ſay, <hi>O but why is the flower of my years cut off by a violent hand?</hi> and this is the ſecond. He dyed of the moſt reproachful death, which in thoſe times was inflicted; that it might not ſeem ſtrange to your Lordſhip, to dy by the hand of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39290:40"/>
                  <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and ſo you might ſay, <hi>O, but why died not I in my cradle, or at least by ſome other natural accident?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Nay, if your Lordſhip will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this death in ſo tender years, you offer him the beſt part of your time. By dying a violent death, you may make that which is neceſſary, to be voluntary; and by dying a diſhonorable death, (taking it as a Penance for your ſins) you may avoid the ſhame of that laſt terrible day. And ſo much the better, you may accept it, becauſe you are not to dy in publique, upon the Bridg, as the ordinary Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom bears, but<note n="(t)" place="margin">It is there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honor, to be put privatly to death. They who dy privat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, dy within the Caſtle, they who publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at the foot of the Bridg.</note> privatly here below, in the Court, as is wont to be uſed towards your Peers.</q> I added alſo ſome other conſiderations, and ſo ended my ſpeech. To which the <hi>Baron.</hi> who was ever ready, made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">How wiſe, the grace of God, is able to make a very yong man, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain!</note> 
               <hi>I, O Father, for as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39290:40"/>much as coneerns the firſt, dy wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly in this freſh age of mine; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thus I ſhall be ſure not to offend my Lord any more. And, from this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, I offer him my years, my age, and my life; and a hundred years, and a hundred ages, and a hundred lives. As for the ſecond; I will make a vertue of neceſſity; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to dy per force, and according to reaſon, I will dy willingly, that ſo I may yield willingly to force, and willingly give ſatisfaction to reaſon, But as for the third; I could wiſh for a more ignominious death. And be you pleaſed to know, that to have dyed in publique, would have given me I know not what increaſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and guſt. For ſo I might have hoped by</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Becauſe publick ſinns re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire publick ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <hi>publique Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to have made a better amends, for my publique crimes. And God knows, I take no contentment, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the favor of dying privatly. But yet however, if the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is made, be ſuch, I reſiſt it not. Our Lord will accept the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39290:41"/>promptitude of my will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon, the <hi>Proveditore</hi> took up the ſpeech, and ſaid: <q>Let your Lordſhip accommodate it ſelf to the will and providence of God, who has not only one way of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving to ſave our Souls, nor one only means of drawing them to him. He leads one by one means, and others by another. It im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports not that<note n="(y)" place="margin">Many of Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſecret but they are all juſt.</note> his Judgments are hidden from us, but it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices that they are juſt. Who can tell, if your Lordſhip ſhould have dy'd in any other ſort then this whether or no, you ſhould have been ſaved?</q> 
               <hi>I am he</hi> (ſaith the Baron) <hi>who can tell you that; for I ſhould have tumbled headlong into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do you not know how God has proceeded with me? It is juſt as a Huntſ-man would do, when he would take a wild beaſt, which he would have brought to his hand, whole and ſound, not torn by the teeth or paws of dogs; nor ſtrucken by the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39290:41"/>bowe, nor bruized by nets, or ſnares; He arivs this beaſt, ſomtimes one way, ſomtimes another, but never lets ſlip the dogs, nor ſhoots the arrow, nor ſpreads the net, or Toyl upon the ground or ſets the ſnare; but, at the moſt, with ſome outcries, or els by throwing ſom ſtones, he rowſeth him, and addreſſeth him towards the place deſigned; and ſo long he drives the beaſt by ſeveral waies, that, at laſt, he brings him thither, where he would have him. The Hunteſ-man knowes this well, and did long expect him there, and he takes him, and enjoys him, all ſound and ſafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Note how wittily, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, he makes this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> 
               <hi>he, O my Good</hi> Jeſus, <hi>who have been this beaſt, hunted hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thither; but thou hadſt a mind, to have me ſafe; thou hadst a mind to have me ſound. And ſo thou didſt not permit, I ſhould be torn with dogs, nor pierced by arrow, nor taken by nets, or Toyles, or ſnares; when thou deliveredſt me out of ſo many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of death, in which, though very young, I have found my ſelf, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39290:42"/>wherein if I had died, without fail, I had periſhed for all eternity: Thou didſt only throw ſtones at me, and cry out after me, when by ſo many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, and inſpirations, thou didſt ſolicite me. And now I repent me, that I was ſo deaf to them. But what mervail, if I were deaf, who after a ſort was</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">By ſinne.</note> 
               <hi>dead? And thus has thy goodnes conducted me to this ſtrait paſs, without my knowing it; that ſo I may be forced to leap into thy lap. For whither am I able to turn my ſelf more ſecurely, then to my dear</hi> Jeſus? <hi>Yea, and though it were in my power, I would not turn any way, but to Thee. It is true, I am forced; but yet I am content withall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the <hi>Confortatori</hi> then <q>replied: It is enough, <hi>Signor Troilo.</hi> So great, and ſo liberal, is the goodneſs of God, that he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts all, and he does it with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. And one of the <hi>Chieſa nuova</hi> ſaid; That, though our Lord received a <hi>Precept,</hi> or <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> that he ſhould dy, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39290:42"/>it is affirm'd, and very true, that he died <hi>voluntarily.</hi>
               </q> And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving accompanied this ſpeech of his, with divers choice examples, one of our Fathers concluded that diſcourſe, with ſhewing, by what means, that which was <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">That puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is impoſed by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, may be made vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, by a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</note> might grow to be <hi>voluntary,</hi> by <hi>a voluntary</hi> accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it: and, that ſo much more it would be <hi>meritorious,</hi> as it ſhould more <hi>willingly</hi> be imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. <hi>Then teach me</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Baron</hi>) <hi>how I may make this enforced death truly voluntary.</hi> Whereupon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain devout, and apt waies how to do it, being declared, by the <hi>Governour</hi> of the <hi>Congregation</hi> of the <hi>Confortatori,</hi> and imbraced by <q>the <hi>Baron,</hi> I ſaid; Perhaps <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> we weary you too much;</q> 
               <hi>How can you weary me?</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Theſe diſcourſes make the night ſhort to me, and my diſaſtre, fortunate.</hi> And here, all were ſilent a while; when he riſing up (for he was ſitting) ſaid, <hi>That he would ſpeak
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39290:43"/>with the father.</hi> And drawing neer me, the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Whom the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company therein.</note> 
               <hi>Confortatori</hi> ſaid the <hi>Confiteor;</hi> and, that being ended, <hi>I deſire</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if it pleaſe you, Father, to call again to mind ſome of the things aforeſaid; both for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter repeting of them, and for the addition of ſome others.</hi> Which I refuſing, out of the aſſurance I had, that it was not neceſſary, he ſaid; <hi>And is it poſſible, dear Father, that you will not give me this laſt contentment? Will you not permit, at leaſt, that I may ſatisfie my ſelf, with confeſſing the offences I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt God? And beſides, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es not your Reverence remember, that we muſt ſpeak together of</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">The Father, it ſeems had made him ſom ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> Penance? I anſwered, Let that <hi>Penance</hi> be, to dy, and to dy well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then teach me that,</hi> ſaid he; And I, thus to him: <q>Offer now, this death of yours, to God, with your whole hart, in penance, for the ſins you have committed.</q> 
               <hi>I do</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>offer it with my heart, and with my mouth; and it grievs me,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39290:43"/>(as our Lord knows) that I have not, this night, a thouſand heads, that in this one of mine, they might be all cut off, and a thouſand lives, that they might all be loſt. Nay</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">How much he gives to God; and how little he thinks it to be; and yet how faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges it all to be of God.</note> 
               <hi>I confeſſe and know, that even that penance, would yet fall ſhort; but ſince more I cannot, more I know not what to do; and ſince more I have not, I can give no more; and even the doing, and giving this little, I acknowledge to proceed from the hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I told him, by way of reply, that it was wel; and that he ſhould ſtil be doing ſo. <q>And when (ſayd I) you are laying your head upon the block, ſay thus in your heart. O Lord, by this act of mine, I proteſt to do penance for my ſins, as if I had a thouſand heads, and thouſand lives; and I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and confeſſe, it is all too little. But I doubt <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> whether then you wil be able to remember this; for at that time perhaps you wil be, as it were, not your ſelf. It is no trifle to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39290:44"/>look death in the face, take my word for that.</q> The magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Lord made this anſwer. <hi>I wil not preſume ſo much upon my ſelf, but</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">He can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faile who putteth all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God, and none in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> 
               <hi>hope wel, and confide greatly in God, that he wil not let it ſlip out of my memory. And if, by any accident, you ſhould perceiv I were unworthy ſo great a grace, doe me the favor to bring me in mind of it; for you ſhall find me ready to put it in execution. In the mean while, I beſeech your Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence tell me ſom what els towards this end of mine, and that quickly, for the time has wings.</hi> I bad him <q>leave the care of that to me. For I will (ſaid <hi>I</hi>) go intimating from time to time, whatſoever you are to think upon; and whatſoever ſhal be ſit for you to ſay, even til your laſt breath.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And<note n="(g)" place="margin">He exhorts him to a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to his good Angel.</note> very now, you ſhall <q>begin to make a ſtrait friendſhip with your <hi>Good Angel.</hi> And firſt ask pardon of him with your hart, for the little gratitude you have expreſſed, for the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39290:44"/>Cuſtody he has afforded you; which has bin ſo inceſſant, ſo patient, ſo diligent, and ſo full of love.</q> Vpon which words, he ſaid (caſting himſelf upon his knees;) <hi>Yea, not only with my mouth, but with my heart, I beg pardon of him, for the very much ingratitude, I have uſed, notwithstanding his ſo great benignity, and love to me;</hi> and ſo kiſſing my knee, he ſate down again. So that I proceeded, and ſaid: Conſider then with your <q>ſelf that your<note n="(h)" place="margin">S Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om ſays expreſly, That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſoul has an <hi>Angelus Cuſtos</hi> aſſingd it by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, from the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of the birth till the laſt of life. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>conc. in</hi> 18. <hi>Mat.</hi> The holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Fathers a bound alſo in proof of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Angels in the help of men.</note> 
                  <hi>good Angel</hi> now is here, who even from your very birth, and ſo much more at this hour, which is ſo full of danger, aſſiſts you, and eſpecially, in ſix particulars. Firſt, he hinders the impetuous aſſaults of the devil, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the force of all thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign ſpirits, who at this inſtant, conſpire to the damnation of your ſoul. Secondly, he brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes into your heart, prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Generoſity, Devotion, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39290:45"/>Contrition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Thirdly, he light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens this darknes, this anguiſh, and this Death. Fourthly, with great ſollicitude, he carries for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and backward, thoſe meſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, which paſſe between God and you; he gathers up your ſighs, your very countenances, and the humiliations of your hart; there is not one of them, which he ſuffers to loſe his way. Fiftly, he negotiates with other Angels of ſuperiour<note n="(i)" place="margin">We read in holy ſcripture (<hi>Dan.</hi> 10.) how one Angel helps an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, for the good of men.</note> Quires, ſo to procure effectual aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for your ſalvation. In moſt particular manner, he moves S. <hi>Michael</hi> the <hi>Archangel,</hi> that he will defend you in this night. Sixtly, he ſollicites my good Angel alſo, that he may procure me to be a competent inſtrument, in this paſſage, which you are making towards your ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Salute him therefore, and ſay <q>thus with me; <hi>Angele Dei,</hi> O<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <hi>He ponders the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er which Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſay dayly, to their good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel:</hi> Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Dei, qui cuſtos es mei, me ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſum, pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tate ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perna, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, cuſtodi, rege, gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> na.</note> thou Angel of God, ſo i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:39290:45"/>known, and ſo ill uſed by me, <hi>qui cuſtos es mei,</hi> who keepeſt me with ſo continual care, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect love, <hi>me tibi commiſſum,</hi> who am committed to thee, being a man ſo faulty, and brought by the providence of God to this paſſage; but yet a ſinner who, by his mercy, and thy prayers, is contrite for his ſins, <hi>pietate ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perna,</hi> by the goodnes of God, for I find no deſert, but cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally confeſſe much demerit, <hi>in hac morte, &amp; hac nocte,</hi> in this death, which is due to me for my offences, and in this laſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of my life, <hi>illumina, cuſtodi, rege, &amp; guberna,</hi> do thou illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, defend, protect, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern me, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This good Noble Man, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat theſe words, with affectuous and abundant tears; and, even by his countenance, one might ſee, his very heart ſplit in his body. And not contenting himſelf, to ſay it once, he would needs repeat
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:39290:46"/>it then, three times; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, he did it again ſo often, the ſame night, as that all the times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, I think, to ten; letting me know withal, that he had not felt greater ſolace, and guſt, in any one ſpiritual Exerciſe, then in this.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Secondly (ſaid I) you ſhall take the glorious Virgin, for your<note n="l" place="margin">To pray for him, as one man may do for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; though all the Saints, &amp; much more, the glorious Mother of God, do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, in a far more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ellent manner.</note> Interceſſor; and then <hi>S. John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and <hi>S. Paul,</hi> who were both condemned to the loſſe of their heads, as your Lordſhip is.</q> 
               <hi>It is true</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>they were condemned as I am; but with this difference; they ſufferd innocent, I for my faults; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I accuſe my ſelf, of ſuch, and ſuch, and ſuch offences, which I have committed againſt God. Which, howſoever I confeſſed before, yet for the reaſons I have already touched, I do willingly repeat.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ended his <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> and received <hi>Abſolution</hi> upon his knees, I deſired him to ſit down again, that the wonted company
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39290:46"/>might come about him.</p>
            <p>And ever, ſome one of them, would be taking up, ſome verſe of the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> which might be appropriated to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion. As,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Viam iniquitatis amove à me, &amp; de lege tua miſerere mei.</l>
               <l>Suſcipe ſervum tuum in bonum, &amp; juſtificationes tuas edoce me.</l>
               <l>Bonum mihi, quia humiliaſti me, ut diſcam juſtificationes tuas.</l>
               <l>Cognovi Domine, quia aequitas judicia tua, &amp; in veritate tua hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaſti me.</l>
               <l>Fiat cor meum immaculatum in juſtificationibus tuis, ut non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundar.</l>
               <l>Miſerere mei Deus, ſecundum magnam miſericordiam tuam; &amp; ſecundum multitudinem miſeratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num tuarum, dele iniquitatem meam</l>
               <l>Erravi ſicut ovis quae perjit, quaere ſervum tuum Domine.</l>
               <l>Deus propitius eſto mihi pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori.</l>
               <l>Deus in audiutorium meum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:39290:47"/>
            <p>And a hundred other, ſuch as theſe; which now, and then, were declared by ſome one of<note n="(m)" place="margin">The <hi>Religious</hi> men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared them. though the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortatori</hi> might repreſent them.</note> us, according to the preſent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein he took much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</p>
            <p>Beſides, he had great comfort, in uſing theſe other Jaculatory Prayers, <hi>Maria Mater gratiae, Mater miſericordiae, Tu nos ab hoſte protege &amp; hora mortis ſuſcipe;</hi> repeating often theſe laſt words, <hi>&amp; hora mortis ſuſcipe.</hi> And again, <hi>Eia ergo advoca noſtra, illos tuos miſericordes oculos ad nos converte, &amp;</hi> Jeſum <hi>benedictum fructum ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris tui, mihi, poſt hanc noctem, oſtende, O clemens, O pia, O dulcis Virgo Maria. Ora pro me pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore indigno, in hac hora mortis meae, Amen, Amen, Amen.</hi> But eſpecially in often, and fervently repeating,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Recordare Jeſu pie,</l>
               <l>Quod ſim cauſa tuae viae,</l>
               <l>Ne me perdas illa die, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In this exerciſe, thoſe brothers,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:39290:47"/>of the <hi>Congregation</hi> of the <hi>Miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia,</hi> were very perfect, and diſcreet; delivering out, in fit times, a great number of theſe verſicles, without importuning, or perplexing him. And ſo alſo did other Religious men, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the occaſion, without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther interrupting one the other, or overwearying the yong Noble man; and they likewiſe exhibited with them certain motives and conſiderations, with much bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, but with great life of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>When theſe things were ended, I ſaid: <q>It will not be amiſs that we recite the <hi>Litanies,</hi> if theſe Gentlemen think it fit.</q> 
               <hi>And I</hi> (ſaid the yong Lord) <hi>if you, and they be ſo pleaſed, will be he that ſhall recite them.</hi> They all made anſwer in the negative, ſaying Your Lordſhip would but weary your ſelf too much. <hi>Nothing leſſe,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>but to me it will be of extream contentment.</hi> And
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:39290:48"/>ſo, (without more diſpute) they put the Book into his hand; and (kneeling, even, by me, againſt a form) he began the <hi>Litanies,</hi> to which we anſwering, <hi>Ora pro eo, Pray for him,</hi> there<note n="o" place="margin">It muſt needs be an object of great compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> was not a man among us, who accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied not the words of his mouth with the tears of his eyes. And eſpecially, when with incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible affection, and devotion, he repeated theſe words, <hi>A mala morte, A poteſtate diaboli, A poenis inferni, libera me Domine. Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver me, O Lord, from an evil death, from the power of the divel, and from the torments of hell.</hi> But<note n="p" place="margin">Nothing but only his ſins could move him to tears.</note> he (O admirable repoſe of mind) did not ſhed one tear. Nay my ſelf, being in tears, who held the candle by him (and not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to repreſſe them) he jogd me with his elbow, and made other ſigns to them, that ſo, giving o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their weeping, they might an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him. And, ſpeaking of it to me afterward, he ſaid, <hi>There
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:39290:48"/>wanted little, of their making him alſo weep, for company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Litanies</hi> were ended, he ſaid, (turning to me) <hi>Father, ſay you the Prayers, over me, that follow.</hi> And then, he taking the candle out of my hand, and give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me the Book, I ſaid thoſe Prayers over him, which are wont to be ſaid, over ſuch as are in their laſt agony; <hi>Commendo</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Theſe a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuous prayers, as any are uſed in the whole of the holy Church, and I wiſh all the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of this, to procure to ſee &amp; read them.</note> 
               <hi>te omnipotenti Deo, &amp;c.</hi> And that other which follows, <hi>Deus miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricors, Deus clemens, &amp;c.</hi> And at the end of theſe, he ſaid with a loud voice, the <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> the <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> the <hi>Credo,</hi> and the <hi>Salve Regina;</hi> and ſo return'd to his ſeat, the others making the accuſtomed circle about him. And ſo one, with repreſenting ſome ſentence of <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſome example, another, ſome other ſpiritual Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we alwaies kept him alive, and quick, and even all kindled in devotion; till ſuch time, as the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:39290:49"/>hour of celebrating <hi>Maſſe</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached.</p>
            <p>Then the Noble Man ſaid thus: <hi>If theſe</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">This ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor is us'd in thoſe parts, for the great inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which have ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>times bin acted in the like extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents.</note> 
               <hi>Manicles are put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to give me pain, or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let the will of my Prince be done, who is pleaſed to have it ſo; but if the meaning be, but to make me ſure; in vain is he tyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, who is bound</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Becauſe his heart was more chain'd, by the love of God, then his hands could be by a load of Iron</note> 
               <hi>within.</hi> Upon which words, all of us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full<note n="t" place="margin">They had great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</note> of tenderneſſe; and in particular one of thoſe <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatori</hi> (who ſhewed himſelf, through the whole night, a moſt compaſſionate Gentleman, in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of this Noble Man) cauſed the Keys to be inſtantly given him, and ſo took the Manicles off; which yet, the <hi>Baron</hi> would needs<note n="u" place="margin">An hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and moſt No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble Soul.</note> kiſſe, and kiſſing them, he ſighed, and ſo held his peace.</p>
            <p>When he had been ſilent a while, and having made a ſign that he deſired to confeſſe again; and when he had bleſſed himſelf, with the ſign of the <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:39290:49"/>
               <note n="x" place="margin">He is much ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous by the memory of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> (ſaid he) <hi>I who have given ſo many diſguſts, and ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ones, to my moſt dear Lady and Mother, through the whole courſe of my life; what comfort does your Reverence think I might be able to give her in my death?</hi> 'By dying well (ſaid I) and in a holy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. To which he anſwer'd thus; <hi>How ſhall the unfortunate woman come to know it?</hi> I told him, I <q>would relate it to her by word of mouth, and in fine I would write it for her; and I will not only notifie it (ſaid I) to her, but to any other whom it may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to know it.</q> 
               <hi>It is enough,</hi> (ſaid he) and he reached his hands out to me, that I might give him one of mine, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, my word. And ſo he kiſſed it often, and holding it between both his, he continued to ſpeak after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I could wiſh, dear Father, that in my place, your Reverence would often viſit and comfort my Lady-Mother,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:39290:50"/>after my death. And when you ſhall ſee her firſt, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you will ask forgivneſſe of her in my name, a thouſand, and a thouſand times, as here I have done, both now, and the other day, ſince I came to priſon. And eſpecially, beg pardon of her, for ſuch, and ſuch a particular offence, and then ſay to her thus;</hi> Your <hi>Troilus</hi> who is dead, begs that bleſſing from your moſt afflicted Ladiſhip, which, being alive, he neither deſerv'd, nor had time to ask. He further recommends the care of his Soul to your Ladiſhip. He praies, he beſeeches, he conjures your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to grant him this his laſt and now only ſuit; that having put your Soul in peace, you will not ſo much as reſent, or call to mind, and much leſſe procure to<note n="y" place="margin">If ſhe thought the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies, whom he had wronged, had proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted him with too much ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſs.</note> revenge your ſelf, for any injury; but that you will remit the whole, and your ſelf withal, to the Eternal Providence of God. <hi>Put her in mind, that it is the part
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:39290:50"/>of a</hi> Roman, <hi>and</hi> Chriſtian <hi>heart, after a generous manner to pardon offences. And, giving her all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, do you aſſure her, that I have particularly reverſed all thoſe irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent words I have formerly uſed towards her; and remembred all thoſe moſt ſweet, dear benefits, I have received from her; and all thoſe Maternal favours, which ſhe has vouchſafed me. And above all, let her know, the inestimable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment I have, to think of the</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">This was a Mother, not only of her ſons bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but of his ſoul alſo.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtian love, ſhe has expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to me, in this laſt paſſage; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever reflecting upon thoſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and great demerits of mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Say to her moreover, that I dy her ſon, and a ſon, who is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly penitent, for all the ill words and deeds I have ever uttered, and perform'd againſt her; and that, in the other world, I will by Gods grace be as grateful to her, as I have been ungrateful here. Relate to her my laſt paſſage, in moſt particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and oblige her, liberally to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:39290:51"/>all my followers, who have been in priſon, upon my account. Of whom, I do, with all the very bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of my heart, ask pardon, for the pain, and peril, wherein to I did ſo idly, and abſurdly caſt them. And aſſure her, in a word, that if for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, yet even for the very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſts I have given her, I ſhall dy content; finding a kind of joy in my heart, that I thus perform this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which I have ſo well deſerved. And ſo, I dying in ſuch ſort, as your Reverence may be pleaſed to let her know, ſhe cannot but receive ſome comfort in my death; and will alſo find, herſelf even engaged, to conform her ſelf to the will of God, as, by his mercy I have done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To my Lady, my</hi> Grand-Mother, <hi>what ſhall I ſay, dear Father? O how compaſſive am I of her great age! What pain does my Soul feel, for that affliction of hers! Give her alſo to underſtand, that I beg par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of her, for ſo many diſguſts, as, in this old age of hers, I have given
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:39290:51"/>her; beſeeching her, in my name, that as long as ſhe lives, ſhe will cauſe a Maſſe every week to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated for my Soul. And in like manner I humbly ask pardon of my Lord</hi> Marqueſſe, <hi>my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle, from the moſt inward parts of my Soul, as I alſo doe of the reſt of my Blood; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching them all to excuſe this youth, or rather ignorance of mine. Putting them alſo in mind that once we ſhall all meet in Heaven. And if ever your Reverence can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to be in my Caſtles, ask pardon, I beſeech you, in my name, of all my vaſſals. Making a promiſe to them, that inſtead of the ill example I have given them, I will not forget them in Heaven, when by the mercy of God, I ſhall be there; and let them in the mean time, excuſe my youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forget not alſo to do this office, with</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">This was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who took his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination</note> Monſignor the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of Rome, <hi>who, about ſome four times, has examined me, with ſo much reſpect and curteſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Give him aſſurance from me, that though
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39290:52"/>my death grieve me, yet I accept it willingly; And beſeech him, that when time ſhall ſerve, he will alſo</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">With how great pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he ſpeaks of the Pope, as he was his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Paſtour, and with obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, as his Prince.</note> 
               <hi>aſſure</hi> our Lord, Pope Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Holineſſe, <hi>that I dy his moſt devoted Son; and moſt ſatisfied with the proceeding of his</hi> Holineſs <hi>towards me. With this moreover, that I am grieved at the very roots of my</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">A noble circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of civility &amp; courteſie.</note> 
               <hi>heart, for having given his</hi> Holineſs <hi>ſo much cauſe of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and grief, eſpecially in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his</hi> Pontificate, <hi>and in the midſt of the joy, which has been expreſſed for his aſſumption to the</hi> Sea Apoſtolique. <hi>And let him be further told, that by placing my ſelf, as I do at your feet, I make accompt I lay my head under the feet of his</hi> Holineſs, <hi>that ſo he might vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to give me his benediction. I having this comfort, in the midſt of all my afflictions, that his ſentence and my death, will ſerve to his whole State, for a lawful, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful example of his Justice. And verily, if it grieve me, at this time,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:39290:52"/>to dy, it alſo grieves me, that even by my death, I am not able to give compleat ſatiisfaction to his</hi> Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>For</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">What a noble ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Soul was this.</note> 
               <hi>as much as he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Father, and Paſtour, cannot, in fine, but feel the death of a Son, and Sheep of his, with diſpleaſure, and grief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon which words, he finding, (even more then before) that there fell ſome tears from mine eyes, to his hands, <hi>This is well indeed,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>your</hi> Reverence <hi>commends my courage; but why then do you weep your ſelf? At least, let not others ſee you.</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd: <q>Do you beleeve, my Son, that I have no ſence in me? Do you think perhaps, I am ſome piece of marble? Proceed you on to the reſt.</q> And then, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divers of his particular friends he deſired me to ask pardon for him, of them all; and this he did, with words of extream ſweetneſs, and prudence. This being then ſaid by him with a moſt admirably
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:39290:53"/>intrepid heart, he concluded with this deſire; <hi>I beſeech your</hi> Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>that in the laſt place, you will beg pardon for me, of Almighty God, as I my ſelf do now, with the moſt internal part of my heart; and of your ſelf, I ask my</hi> Penance <hi>and</hi> Abſolution.</p>
            <p>Which as ſoon as I had given him, the Brothers of that <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> of the <hi>Miſericordia,</hi> did put us in mind that it was time <hi>Maſſe</hi> ſhould be celebrated; and ſo the Prieſt, as ſoon as he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, began. The devout yong Lord, and I kneeling together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a form, he ſaid thus to me. <hi>The Prieſt is beginning</hi> Maſſe; <hi>and I (with your good leave) will have a new</hi> Reconciliation, <hi>according to that, which my good Angel ſhall bring to my remembrance, of whom I have deſired this favour.</hi> The <hi>Prieſt</hi> was ſaying the <hi>Confiteor</hi> at the foot of the <hi>Altar;</hi> to whom one of the <hi>Congregation</hi> (making anſwer) was ſo overwrought with
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:39290:53"/>tenderneſs, that he could not get to the end of it; in ſuch ſort, as that it was neceſſary, ſome other ſhould do it for him. Then the good Noble Man, who anſwered ſoftly to the <hi>Confiteor,</hi> leaning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, ſaid thus, <hi>Give</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">He had the gift of tears in a ſtrange meaſure.</note> 
               <hi>me leave to weep, whileſt I ſay the</hi> Confiteor, <hi>ſince that Gentleman weeps ſo bitterly, to whoſe office it belongs not greatly, that he ſhould</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>weep.</hi> I anſwer'd, he might weep in the name of God; ſince he had given him ſuch great deſire ſo to do. And it was an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble effect of divine grace, that inſtantly, I ſaw the tears ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down his cheeks, and pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelves, even upon the cuſhion, that lay before him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Confiteor</hi> was don, &amp; all<note n="f" place="margin">Till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Goſpel.</note> the while the <hi>Prieſt</hi> was read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a loud voice, he did not move at al, but wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moſt fixedly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive, &amp; as it were rapt towards the<note n="g" place="margin">The <hi>Crucifix</hi> was of ſtone, but his mind was upon the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, not upon the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, not upon the picture.</note> 
               <hi>Crucifix,</hi> upon the <hi>Altar,</hi> which was there moſt devoutly
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:39290:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>made. And ſhortly after, (turning towards my ear) he accuſed himſelf of divers little things, which then ſuddenly ſurpriz'd his mind. And the <hi>Prieſt</hi> being com to<note n="h" place="margin">About the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Maſſe.</note> 
               <hi>Surſum corda; Father</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>do you think indeed, that by ſuch a death as this, and ſo well deſerved, I may yet go</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>ſtrait to heaven?</hi> And why (ſaid I) may not your Lordſhip under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe this death with ſo great and ſo wel condition'd affectuouſneſs of mind, as that your ſoul may be ſure to fly up inſtantly, from the block, into heaven.</q> 
               <hi>O my God!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>And what kind of affectuouſneſs muſt that be! O teach it me a little! O, that our Lord would grant it me!</hi> Pray (ſaid I) <q>very earneſtly unto him for it, and peradventure he will grant it</q> At which time, the <hi>Priest</hi> being in the very act of the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the Body of our Lord,</hi> the yong Noble Man ſpake theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, very words. <hi>O bone Jeſu, ſis mihi, in hac hora, Jeſus. O dear
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:39290:54"/>Lord Jeſus, be thou, in this hour, a Jeſus to me.</hi> And this he ſaid, with ſo ardent affection of mind, though with a low voice, as that after it, he was wholly immove-able, till the <hi>Prieſt</hi> went on, to<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Domine non ſum dignus, &amp;c.</hi> And then, he ſaid thus to me. <hi>I have not, Father, been attentive, either when the</hi> Pater Noſter, <hi>or the</hi> Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Dei, <hi>was ſaid; may</hi> I <hi>yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs communicate?</hi> I anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that for the preſent, he ſhould do ſuch a<note n="k" place="margin">This was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the knocking of his breaſt, or ſome ſuch other thing, which might be done at the inſtant</note> Penance, whileſt I was giving him <hi>Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Which being done, he went, of himſelf, to the <hi>Altar;</hi> and kneeling down, did with exemplar devotion, receive the <hi>most Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament;</hi> and ſoon after, he came back, towards me where he remain'd, without any motion at all.</p>
            <p>After this, turning about to all thoſe who aſſiſted, he ſaid, <hi>I give thanks to you all, for your Charity, and courteſie; and, I beſeech you,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:39290:55"/>pardon the painful night I have brought upon you.</hi> And then, he deſired me, for the love of him, to repeat thoſe words, to every one of them, in particular; and ſo I did. Being then intreated to ſit down, the wonted circle was made about him. Where every one endeavour'd to animate him, towards the combat then at hand; by repreſenting the ſhortneſs of the pain, the immenſity of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the vanity of the world; and above all, the abundant grace, which, in the ſpace of ſo few hours, our Lord had communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Soul, and had given him withall, ſuch a pregnant ſign of his <hi>Predeſtination;</hi> wherein the Noble Youth ſeem'd to find ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary guſt.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the many diſcourſes which were made to this purpoſe, as well by the <hi>Confortatori,</hi> as by <q>our Fathers, I uſed this. And what think you, <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> will the grace, which God hath
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:39290:55"/>given you, be ſufficient to make you bear this puniſhment? I tell you truly, that in imitation of Chriſt, you ſhould do well to deſire it, and that deſire, would ſerve to make it more tolerable to you; Nay it would make it ſeem no puniſhment at all, and laſtly it would make it ſeem ſwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</q> As it hapned to Chriſt our Lord himſelf, to<note n="m" place="margin">The immenſe love which our Lord Jeſus bare to man, made all he ſuffered ſeem little to him.</note> whom his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> ſeem'd ſo ſmall a matter, that whereas others cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, by the name of a huge thing, an <hi>Ocean,</hi> a deep ſea, <hi>(Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni in altitudinem maris, &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtas demerſit me)</hi> himſelf <q>calls it, but a Cup ful; <hi>(Calicem quem dedit mihi Pater, non vis ut bibam illum?)</hi> Again, after that huge heap of bitterneſs, and torments which he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd, it ſeem'd nothing to him. For being ask'd by thoſe diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples who were going to <hi>Emaus.</hi> if he knew of that vaſt cruelty, which had then lately bin
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:39290:56"/>executed at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> upon the perſon of the greateſt Saint of God, he anſwer'd, by asking, <hi>Quae?</hi> for in fine he eſteem'd it all as nothing. Therefore, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> he uſed the word <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Baptiſmo habeo baptizari, &amp; quomodo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arctor,</hi> &amp;c. And you know that <hi>bathes</hi> ſerve for delicacy. What ſay you then <hi>Signor Troilo?</hi> Does not your puniſhment, by this time, ſeem ſmall to you?</q> 
               <hi>Small;</hi> (ſaith he?) <hi>it ſeems no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Yet can I not ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, either that it is nothing, or yet very pleaſant; but nevertheleſs, it is dear to me, and as ſuch I prize it. And</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">How mightily this noble man, grew up in grace, even by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> 
               <hi>I aſſure you, at the preſent, it would be as it were, a kind of trouble for me, to eſcape it. Before I deſired to eſcape; I ſighed for it; I labour'd for it; and I know not what of that kind. But I had not then, that knowledge of my ſelf, which now, by the favor of God, methinks I have, in ſuch ſort, as now, I can
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:39290:56"/>affirm to you, in the word of Truth, that I</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">This ſo ardent deſire, of ſuffering for his ſins, muſt needs be a great diſpoſition towards the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pardon for them, through the mercy of Chriſt our Lord.</note> 
               <hi>deſire my end, how pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſoever it may be, towards the remiſſion of my ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this, another Father ſaid; <q>your Lordſhip ſpeaks wiſely; for God knows, whether other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, you ſhould ever have bin ſo well prepared for death.</q> Whereupon, one of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortatori</hi> proceeded thus, If your <q>Lordſhip had dyed naturally in your bed; what, with the pain of your body, and the anguiſh of your mind; it may be you would ſcarce have been maſter of your ſelf. And if you had dyed, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other accident, perhaps you would not have had time, to bring forth, ſo much as the name of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Whereas now, it<note n="(p)" place="margin">Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing firſt, the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ce of God, as is declared afterward.</note> is in a manner, in your own power, to dy as well as you will your ſelf, with what dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of your ſins you will; with what love of Chriſt you will; and, in a word, in that beſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:39290:57"/>manner, which the grace of Almighty God will impart to you; which we perceive, even ſo to overflow your Soul, that we are as much aſtoniſhed, as comforted, by the knowledge of it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hereunto the conſtant Noble Man made this anſwer. <hi>You ſhall know, that by the goodneſs of God, I find in my ſelf, no trouble nor ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and me</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the very hand of God, was able ſo to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted him, through theſe ſtony waye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And it ſeems, God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, in a very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular manner.</note> 
               <hi>thinks I am in a hand which hears me up. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and I reſolve to dy, in that manner, which I ſhall be taught to be the beſt; and I am moſt ready, for the ſaving of my Soul, to obey whatever ſhall be commanded me.</hi> This, ſaid I, you ſhall therefore do. You ſhall bar your ſelf in <q>that hour, of ſome eaſe. That is, you ſhall for the love of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and, in imitation of what he did &amp; ſuffered for you, deprive your ſelf of ſomewhat, which you might have; and which, at that time, might be agreeable to you.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:39290:57"/>For, if you well remember, they gave twice unto our Lord, to drink. The firſt time, when they gave him <hi>vinegar,</hi> he drank; but when they gave him wine, as ſoon as he had taſted it, he put it by. But do you know the reaſon? It was this. To ſuch as were condemned to dy, it was the cuſtom to give wine, with an infuſion of <hi>myrrhe;</hi> that by the comfort of it they might faint the leſs, under their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Now our Lord (who was pleaſed to deprive himſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, and fully, of all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for love of us, and for our example) refuſed that, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepred the <hi>vinegar,</hi> which was mingled with<note n="(r)" place="margin">With Gall.</note> another moſt bitter ingredient; that ſo he migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the moſt he could, for our example, and benefit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Providitore</hi> ſaid. <q>that this was moſt certainly true; whereupon ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expound thoſe words, which Chriſt ſpake
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:39290:58"/>upon the <hi>croſs, Deus Deus m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ut quid dereliquiſti me?</hi> That Chriſt our Lord, did grieve thereat, becauſe the <hi>Divinity</hi> beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, as it were, to hide it ſelf from the <hi>Humanity;</hi> and conſequently by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, his life was leaving him; and by occaſion thereof, he was able to ſuffer no longer; which the moſt en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mor'd Jeſus obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, complain'd of it, to his <hi>Father,</hi> by the words afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe things a Father of ours, adding other devour, and ſhort diſcourſes, the <hi>Confortatori</hi>
               <q>ſaid; That for the time his Soul was ſufficiently fed; and that it would be well done, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh his body.</q> The Baron an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>there was no need of that.</hi> But they preſſing it much, there was brought in ſome wine by a ſervant of the Lord<note n="(s)" place="margin">This Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is the place of greateſt confidence the Pope beſtows.</note> 
               <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of the <hi>Caſtle,</hi> which, one of the Gentlemen there preſent,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:39290:58"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring forth into a glaſs, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Baron;</hi> who ſaid again, it was wholly needleſs; <hi>And yet</hi> (ſaid he, turning then towards me) <hi>if I ſhould need it, your</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">A good memory he had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a more pious will.</note> 
               <hi>Reverence told me a while ago, that in imitation of Chriſt, I ſhould do well to deprive my ſelf of it. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is it not ſo?</hi> Nevertheleſs being intreated by all the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that he would drink, or at leaſt, ſo much, as waſh his mouth; this laſt he did twice, without ſwallowing any wine at all. And this was ſo much more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe ſuch as are in that caſe, uſe to be extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken with thirſt, which is held to be one of their greateſt tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>The wine being then carried away, divers queſtions were ask'd this moſt illuſtrious Lord, to which he<note n="(u)" place="margin">Note and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at theſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, which are ſo full of piety, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and courage,</note> anſwered with ſo great prudence and judgement, that more could not be imagin'd. He was asked firſt (for, of many,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:39290:59"/>I will mention only a few, &amp; this firſt queſtion he was asked often) <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> will your Lordſhip have any thing? He ſtill anſwer'd, <hi>that he deſired nothing,</hi> ſaving that once he held his deace, but made a ſign up to heaven. Beſides, he was often asked, <hi>Signor Troile,</hi> of what are you thinking? Sometimes he anſwered, <hi>upon nothing in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular;</hi> Sometimes, <hi>upon our Lord;</hi> Sometimes upon my ſins; Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, <hi>upon my approaching end;</hi> Sometimes, he ſaid, <hi>I think upon the ſo many gifts, which God has beſtowed upon me, and that</hi> I <hi>have been ſo very ungrateful, yea and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unmindful of them all.</hi> Being then asked in this manner, Does <q>your Lordſhip dy willingly? He anſwered:</q> 
               <hi>And what? would you have me buſtle againſt the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Prince? Or ſhould</hi> I <hi>not be content, with the providence, and</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>good pleaſure of God?</hi> Is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſaid one, that the Devil ſhould not ſtrive, to make you
<pb facs="tcp:39290:59"/>think your death unjuſt?</q> I <hi>do not,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>eſteem it only to be juſt; but moſt juſt; and as for the Divel,</hi> I <hi>neither have, nor will have, any more to do with him,</hi> I <hi>have had enough, and too much of him already.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Another asked him, what he ſaid of the Lady his Mother, his Friends, his Kindred, and himſelf; if he were not much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the thought thereof?</q> 
               <hi>Concerning my Lady Mother</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I confeſs, in the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts of my heart,</hi> I <hi>find ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme affliction; but, on the other ſide</hi> I <hi>rejoyce that</hi> I <hi>am paying the offences,</hi> I <hi>have committed againſt her, with my bloud. And</hi> I <hi>hope, the readineſs wherewith</hi> I <hi>imbrace this Penance, for my wicked car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wards her, will be ſo well accepted by Almighty God, that he may, through his goodneſs, give her no ſmall comfort, even by this very death of mine.</hi> I <hi>think of my kindred with grief, as having been
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:39290:60"/>a cauſe of Sorrow and trouble to them; of my friends as having given them ill example; of my ſelfe,</hi> I <hi>take no care; for behold who</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">A great faith, &amp; hope, &amp; love.</note> 
               <hi>does it for me;</hi> making a ſign towards the <hi>Crucifix,</hi> which he had hard by him.</p>
            <p>Being asked, whether the time did ſeem long to him or ſhort. <hi>Neither</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">This I find to be a ſtrange anſwer, in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee of ſtrangenes.</note> 
               <hi>long</hi> (ſay he) <hi>nor ſhort.</hi> And another replying to him thus; Is it poſſible, that you are not griev'd, you muſt die; I <hi>do not,</hi> ſays he, <hi>deny, but I am grievd at it, but yet it neither troubles me, nor ſo much, as alters me, more then you ſee.</hi> It being wiſhed, that he ſhould ſuffer his chair to be drawn a litle forward, that ſo he might ſit at greater eaſe; <hi>To what end (ſaid he) ſhould I give my body eaſe, I am wel here; &amp; with the help of God, I ſhall be ſhortly free from needing that, or any thing elſe.</hi> Being deſired to raiſe, &amp; reſt his feet, upon a place of advantage, where they uſed to kneel, that ſo he might be in a more
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:39290:60"/>commodious poſture; he ſaid, (drawing near my ear,) <hi>Father, it is a piece of ill manners, to ſit with a mans legs raised up, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of others.</hi> But I adviſing him however, that he would ſet them up; he did inſtantly accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date himſelf to my deſire.</p>
            <p>Being asked to what devotions "he had bin moſt particuler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: He anſwer'd; <hi>Above all the Saints in Heaven, to that of our</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">He was ever much devo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to our B. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed Lady, in whoſe honour, I did daily recite her Office, but with an impure mouth; and how then could that be accepted by her? And till within theſe two years, I made,</hi> ſaid he <hi>much account of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Confeſſion, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch through the mercy of my Lord, I reſolv'd ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to intermit, unleſſe it were by ſome very unlucky accident, that ſhould interpoſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelf. And I ever carried living in my heart, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of many things which former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, upon ſeveral occaſions, had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en repreſented to me by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:39290:61"/>Fathers, with whom I had much converſed,</hi> (inſinuating ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as I conceive, the Fathers of the <hi>Chieſa Nuova.</hi>) <hi>And, When I had means, to do it in private, I never failed any day, to ſalute the Bleſſed Virgin upon my bare knees.</hi> And then, I ſaying (I know not well, upon what occaſion) <hi>Ah poor Signor Troilo. Poor</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I was, when I was without the the grace of my Lord God, but now I take myſelf to he rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then the time of his end drawing on apace, we riſing up from our ſeats, did encircle him upon our knees. And (after the manner of two Quires, interch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geably anſwering one another) we began the ſeven <hi>Penitential Pſalms;</hi> pondering ſome of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes now &amp; then, &amp; cauſing him to reſume divers of them. They being ended, he was adviſed to ſay often <hi>Recordare Jeſu pie</hi> &amp;c. And then<note n="(a)" place="margin">Theſe are parts of ſome <hi>Hymns</hi> which are recited by the holy Church, in honour of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and our B. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</note> 
               <hi>Eia ergo advocata noſtro &amp;c.</hi> And then again <hi>Maria mater gratiae,</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:39290:61"/>and the like. Which he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, with ſo clear a voice, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant a memory, and with a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſo ſerene, that all who were preſent (himſelf only exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted) did weep outright; Which he obſerving made ſilence, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his own face into his hands, ſtood ſtill a while, in mental pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; And then, turning towards me, ſaid; <hi>Confitcor</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">The enatrance whereby we begin to make our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Deo Omnipotenti &amp; tibi Pater. I accuſe my ſelf of this and this, and that;</hi> Ideo<note n="(c)" place="margin">This we uſe to ſay when we have ended it.</note> precor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then, inſtantly he added this: <hi>Father I would deſire</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">A far greater matter it was to ask this ſuit, then to grant it.</note> 
               <hi>this laſt favour of you, that you would confeſs me at the block; and that, whilſt I, on the one ſide, with my Beads in my hand, might ſay</hi> O bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Jeſu, ſis mihi Ieſus; <hi>O good Lord Jeſus, be thou a Jeſus to me; &amp; you on the other,</hi> Ego te abſolvo, &amp;c. I <hi>abſolve thee, &amp;c. at the ſame inſtant the iron might fall upon my neck.</hi> Not ſo, my Lord, ſaid I. For ſo by giving a ſign to the Executioner for
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:39290:62"/>the cutting off your head, I ſhould becom<note n="(e)" place="margin">By the <hi>canons</hi> of the holy Church, a Prieſt may not coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to the death of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo far off; but on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents in courſe of Juſtice; nor then neither, but with particular diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that in very rare caſes. The <hi>Inquiſition</hi> has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do herein, but only examines and leaves ſuch as are faulty and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent to the ſecular Judges.</note> 
               <hi>Irregular.</hi> No, no I will not do it, by any means. But then, obſerving he was much afflicted by my negative, and ſo rather to quiet him, then for any thing elſe, I ſaid it might perhaps be thus better done, you may <hi>confes</hi> at the block, &amp; being confeſſed, you may begin to <q>invoke the name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and when I ſhall ſee the Executioner ready to let down the iron, I may ſay with a lowd voice, <hi>Ego te ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvo. &amp;c.</hi> Yet perhaps again this would be more inconvenient, for by giving you a ſign, when the iron were upon the point of falling, it might fright you in ſuch ſort, that if by the motion of your body; it ſhould not fall juſt upon your neck it would mangle you, and ſo afflict you with a double pain, &amp; a double death, I will not do it by any means.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At theſe words, caſting his head
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:39290:62"/>upon my boſom, he ſaid; <hi>Ah Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even by all the love you bear this miſerable ſinfull Soul, do me this favor; I make a promiſe to you in the name, and by the help of God, that you ſhall not put me into terror by it. For Gods love believe me; I beſeech you give me credit.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon yet, I continuing, as I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved before; <hi>O God</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>and might not thy divine Majeſty move the heart of this my Father, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem me worthy this favor?</hi> Well, be of courage (ſaid I, to quiet him) I promiſe you that I will do it. <hi>Then give me</hi> (anſwer'd he) <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">The hands of Catholick Prieſts are anointed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated with great ſolemnity</note> 
               <hi>ſacred hand of yours.</hi> And I gave it him, with this purpoſe, that if he ſhould not remember it, at the block, as I verily though he would not, then I would let it paſs; and that if h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> remembred it, and did franckly cal for it, I would perform it. But it ſeemd (as I ſaid) to me, that a man co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld hardly be of ſo undanted a mind, as that, in ſo hard a paſſage, his memory
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:39290:63"/>would ſerve him for ſuch a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; &amp; that, whereas all men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to divert their minds from ſuch a blow, this <hi>Baron</hi> would needs have an expreſs ſign of it. But in fine, where the grace of God enters, it produces effects, which far outſtrip all the power of nature and no wit of man arrives to them.</p>
            <p>When I had made him this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; I<note n="(g)" place="margin">His heart wrought mightily towards humility.</note> 
               <hi>would know</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your</hi> Reverence <hi>will not think it ſit that I give thanks, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand pardon of thoſe who have had moſt to do with me in this place.</hi> I told him I liked well of it; &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given him <hi>Abſolution,</hi> I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him by a ſign to ſit down. Then he ſaid <hi>Father, take you care of my journy from hence to the block, as you have already promiſed; &amp; you ſhall pleaſe to go advertiſing me from pace to pace of ſuch things as are fit, that I may have my whole ſoul for God alone.</hi> I will advertiſe you, (ſaid I) of all, keep your ſelf prepared, and ſit down.</p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:39290:63"/>
            <p>As ſoon as he was ſet, all the ſtrings of our very hearts ſeemd to be moved at once, to pray him that he would be mindfull of us in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And<note n="(h)" place="margin">It is a ſign they ſaw ſtrange tokens of Gods favor in him.</note> every one of us there preſent, both with words &amp; tears, did recommend himſelf to him the beſt he could; &amp; we were not able to ſatisfie our ſelves in the deſire we had of expreſſing kindneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him. And verily this was a death of ſo much tenderneſs, that the remembrance of it at this time affects me at the very Soul. Only the young Noble Man remain'd with a moſt Angelical Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and with a heart which ſeem'd not ſo much as to know what belong'd to fear.</p>
            <p>This<note n="(i)" place="margin">A de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iption of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnor Troilo</hi>'s perſon and faſhion.</note> 
               <hi>Sig. Troilo</hi> was tall of ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, of delicate conſtitution; of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour rather olivaſter then very fair, of black hair &amp; thick, of face neither fat not lean, his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es were black, &amp; ful, and quick his noſe ſweetly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: his mouth of a juſt proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and rather, ſmiling, then
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:39290:64"/>otherwiſe; his forehead compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently ſpatious and he had not ſo much as one ſingle hair upon his cheeks. Of a ſweet voice, of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy anſwers; and ſo compleat in good faſhion, that, even at the block, he failed not to ſalute, and reſalute all men, according to the occaſion, and their condition; and, not being able to take off his hat himſelf, to make others do it for him.</p>
            <p>It hapned once, that I deſired him to let me wipe his face with a handkerchief; not that he was in any ſweat, but only to refreſh him a little: He ſuffer'd me to begin to do him that ſervice, and then ſaid; <hi>Father, I need not this.</hi> But I deſired, that at leaſt he would rub his face with his own hands, for it would refreſh him; and inſtantly doing ſo, he ſaid to me in mine ear; <hi>Father,</hi> I <hi>had an extreme deſire to ſtretch my ſelf, but methought it had ſomewhat of the Clown.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:39290:64"/>
            <p>In concluſion, he cauſed all thoſe ſouldiers, who had kept guard over him, to paſs before him one by one; and ſo<note n="(k)" place="margin">It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue ſign, and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain fruit of true penance, to ſubmit a mans ſelf mightily for Gods ſake.</note> caſting himſelf upon his knees to every one of them as they ſingly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed, he asked pardon moſt humbly of them, with Noble and Chriſtian words; and he left them alſo libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral donatives. To the Gentleman <hi>Porter</hi> he did the like, and more; excuſing himſelf for the trouble he had given him.</p>
            <p>But now there remained no more to be done, the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing run out; For the<note n="(l)" place="margin">In thoſe Countries there rings a bell eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, noon, and night, when all men recite three ſhort prayers, in remembrance of the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Chriſt our Lord. This they do whereever they be, when the bell rings, though it be in the ſtreets; and there they ſalute one other, with a wiſh of the good day, or night.</note> 
               <hi>Ave Maria</hi> bell did ſound. Upon the hearing whereof we all recited that Prayer, and he ſaid it alſo upon his knees. Then ſaluting all the company, he ſate down, and was ſilent. And whileſt he held his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:39290:65"/>peace, we ſpake among our ſelves with aſtoniſhment at many things we had obſerved in him, and they were theſe: He did never ſweat, nor ever complain'd of any thing. He never placed himſelf with any ſhew of wearineſs upon his chair; nor ever ſhew'd any unquietneſs. He never wept, but whilſt he was making his Confeſſion; nor ever ſought to eaſe himſelf in the courſe of Nature. He never had any thirſt; nor ever fainted. He was never ſleepy; nor ever over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought with ſorrow. He was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver freſh and ſtrong; though in that night he had bin ſo many and very many times upon his knees. He ever anſwer'd readily, and with a lively voice. His memory never failed, or ſo much as wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. He was handſomly and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly apparell'd. He<note n="(m)" place="margin">A ſtrange image of perfection was this young No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man.</note> ſpake not ſo much as an inconſiderate word. He never expreſſed a deſire of any thing. He had at certain times, and upon certain occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:39290:65"/>a diſcharged and ſmiling countenance. He did compleatly give every man thoſe titles of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which were his due; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out failing ſo much as once; as to one, of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verence,</hi> to another of <hi>Honour;</hi> to another, of <hi>You.</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared moſt currently his laſt <hi>Will,</hi> which was a ſheet of paper long. He was not taken by paſſionate tenderneſs, but only upon the ſpeech of the Lady his Mother. He ſpake moſt honourably and Chriſtianly of the Prince and Judges; and even of thoſe who proſecuted the cauſe againſt him. All which particulars, or the moſt part of them happen otherwiſe in others who fall into the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. So that all thoſe old ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced <hi>Confortatori</hi> of that <hi>Congregation</hi> of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſericordia</hi> were amazed to ſee how abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly the grace of God had wrought upon that Soul in the ſpace of a few hours.</p>
            <p>When this moſt devout No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:39290:66"/>man had thus held his peace, and we had been diſcourſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves of the things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, he, calling me towards him, who yet was ſtanding not far off, ſpake to me in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Dear Father, let us make our laſt Reconciliation with God.</hi> And then he made a ſhort recapitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all his faults; and began<note n="(n)" place="margin">A hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſoul to be ſo ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and ſo intirely purified.</note> to accuſe himſelf of things ſo extreamly ſmall; as gave occaſion and matter to this Soul of mine, even till this day wherein I write, and will till the hour of my death, both to be comforted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded.</p>
            <p>Being upon the end of his Confeſſion he fell into a moſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent weeping; in ſuch ſort, as that bowing down his head towards my hand, I was not able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the heat of his breath. And <q>when I ſaid to him, <hi>Troilo</hi> my Son; Caſt a bridle upon thoſe tears of yours; do not exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate your own wound; it is now
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:39290:66"/>enough, and again enough; you have wept enough, you will have time to weep yet again, when you come to lay your Head upon the block, for <note n="(o)" place="margin">He was to ſuffer death for his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de eds, but he was to bear it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently and willingly for the love of Chriſt.</note> Chriſt.</q> His anſwer was this; I <hi>have already told you, Father, and now</hi> I <hi>tell you once again,</hi> I <hi>weep for my ſins, not for my death. And when your</hi> Reverence <hi>ſhall have given me</hi> Abſolution, <hi>and</hi> I <hi>have perform'd the</hi> Penance <hi>you will impoſe (which only deſerves to be accompanied with tears) you ſhall find</hi> I <hi>will weep no more.</hi> And juſt ſo it hapned; for, wiping his face when I had <hi>abſolved</hi> him, and I having acquainted him with ſome neceſſities of mine own, to the end he might give me<note n="(p)" place="margin">By his holy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</note> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in the ſight of our Lord; he remain'd with eyes as full of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity, and void of tears, as if in all his life he had never wept.</p>
            <p>But then having rais'd himſelf, it was thought fit by all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:39290:67"/>that certain <hi>Pſalms</hi> ſhould be repeated, whereof I, with the <hi>Confortator<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> were to ponder ſome of the verſes till ſuch time as his hour ſhould arrive. Whereupon he ſaid, <hi>It is now broad day, and there cannot be much time remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Our</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">Great Piety and gratitude.</note> 
               <hi>Lord be bleſſed for making me paſs through this night ſo happily and ſo holily.</hi> I <hi>thank you dear Father, and you Gentlemen, for your ſo great favor. The good God reward you for it.</hi> And here all of us recommending our ſelves again to his prayers, we alſo again began the Pſalms.</p>
            <p>At this time the <hi>Executioner</hi> came in, and no man had the heart to tell my Lord of it; but he, perceiving there was a preaſs of people, gently turn'd his face about, and as ſoon as he had ſet eye upon him, he was not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with it at all; but<note n="(r)" place="margin">Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauored holy cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</note> arm'd himſelf only with the ſign of the <hi>Holy Croſs;</hi> and, making a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:39290:67"/>to me, who ſtood cloſe by him, he roſe and ſaid: <hi>Well, the hour is come; Gentlemen, let us go, and that cheerfully.</hi> And, they all anſwering thus; <q>Yea let it be done cheerfully, <hi>Signor Troilo,</hi> cheerfully for the love of <hi>Jeſus;</hi>
               </q> He turn'd towards the <hi>Executioner,</hi> who kneeling down at his feet to ask his pardon; <hi>Do y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur office</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>in the name of God, for ſo He will have it.</hi> Your Lordſhip (ſaid he) is to unbutton the Coller of your doublet; And he (being as ready on the one ſide, as he was modeſt on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) with his own hands began to unbutton. <q>It is not enough, ſaid the chief <hi>Execution<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> the doublet muſt be put off:</q> But the reſt of thoſe Officers of <hi>Juſtice</hi> were not willing he ſhould put it off: Yet the generous No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man ſaid, <hi>That, however he would do it, if they thought it fit. For</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>it ſhall not greatly
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:39290:68"/>trouble me; and if you have a mind to it,</hi> I <hi>will ſtrip my ſelf from head to foot for the love of God.</hi> Already therefore he was begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to unty himſelf; but it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed that he was unbutton'd to the ſhoulders. Then one of the <hi>Confortatori</hi> putting him in mind of <hi>Non crubeſcam, &amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>Officer</hi> coming to tie his arms in ſuch a faſhion, as that when he ſhould be arrived at the block, his body might not have much leave to move; <hi>In the name of God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>bind hoth my arms, and my hands too, if your will be ſuch. For</hi>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">This man had true faith in Chriſt our Lord, and his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, who in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, was ſo willing to ſuffer, as you ſee.</note> 
               <hi>my Lord Jeſus was yet much worſe bound for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being therefore thus accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated, they caſt a gown about him; and he kneel'd down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Altar;</hi> in act, as if he had craved a benediction at the hands of our Lord. And, without the leaſt change of colour, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Pſalm <hi>Miſerere</hi> of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:39290:68"/>and, being come as far as the outward room, he pauſed there with an incredible decency and grace; And ſaid to ſome of the by-ſtanders, <hi>Might</hi> I <hi>not thank my Lord, the Governour of the Caſtle before</hi> I <hi>dy?</hi> But they preſenting I know not what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of his not being riſen, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted thereof, and commanded a Gentleman who ſerved the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> to thank him in his name. And, having demanded pardon of many of the Aſſiſtants, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them, in ſome very few words, to vertue, by the example, which there they had before their eies of the contrary, he went on with the very ſame verſe of the <hi>Miſerere,</hi> where he had left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And ſometimes turning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, he would be ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Come</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">See whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid of death or no.</note> 
               <hi>Father, come; to heaven to heaven.</hi> And it was a ſtrang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thing, that he being in pantofl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and going down ſuch a long pair
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:39290:69"/>of ſtairs, as that is; and much broken by reaſon of the Artillery, which, upon frequent occaſions, is drawn up and down them, yet did not his foot once ſlip; Though I, who was in ſhoos, failing to tread right many times, was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him to take care of my ſelf.</p>
            <p>When he was arriv'd to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther open ſtairs, where many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the <hi>Caſtle</hi> were to ſee him; one of the <hi>Confortatori,</hi> who was well experienced in thoſe occaſions, and ſtood on the one hand, placing a <hi>Crucifix</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him (and as it were covering him therewith) cried out with a ſtrong voice, <hi>Let</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">Viva Gieſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Jeſus live;</hi> be not frighted, my Lord. To which he (after he had ended the Verſe he was pronouncing) made this anſwer; <hi>Yea let Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus live; in whom whilſt</hi> I <hi>am hoping,</hi> I <hi>fear not to be confounded.</hi> And then ſaid I, <hi>In te Domine ſperavi,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:39290:69"/>non confundar in aeternum;</hi> which being repeated by him, he ſpake thus to them; <hi>Take</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">A no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix <hi>aſide; let all the people ſee me. For, if</hi> I <hi>be good for nothing elſe, at leaſt</hi> I <hi>may ſerve them for an example.</hi> There paſſed one that way with a bottle of wine in his hand, who ſaluted the <hi>Baron</hi> upon his knee, and the <hi>Baron</hi> courteouſly reſaluted him; and ſo return'd to the ſame verſe of the <hi>Pſalm,</hi> which he had formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun. Soon after, paſſing through the people who ſtood there ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what thick, he ſaid; <hi>Learn</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">Few words, and well cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. It is not there the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for a man to ſtand preaching at the place of his execution.</note> 
               <hi>by my example to live well, and pray for me.</hi> And thus with <hi>Pſalms</hi> and <hi>Jaculatory prayers</hi> he came to the block, where there was ſtore of lookers on.</p>
            <p>The intrepid <hi>Baron</hi> pauſing there, ſaid thus. <hi>I would deſire in theſe laſt moments of my life to ſee at least, and ſalute and thank the Lieutenant Governour of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:39290:70"/>ſince I cannot ſee my Lord the Governour.</hi> But the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> by no means reſolving to go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him (for the extreme ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs wherewith he was taken) the Noble Youth perceiving it, and turning to me, ſaid; <hi>Father, his heart ſerves him not to come; and perhaps</hi> I <hi>make the people ſtay too long.</hi> O moſt valiant and moſt undaunted mind, which was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled more with the ſlight incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of others, then with the apprehenſion of his own immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent death!</p>
            <p>At laſt he cheerfully advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing forward, the <hi>Lieutenant</hi> came before him; and the <hi>Baron</hi> caſting himſelf upon his knee, ſaid to me, <hi>In courteſie, Father, take off my hat:</hi> Which the good Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman obſerving,<note n="z" place="margin">A kind contention who ſhould moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in courteſie.</note> did with a moſt bitter and loud cry of tears even ſpread himſelf all upon the ground; and all the by-ſtanders upon that occaſion did caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:39290:70"/>upon their knees; nor was there any thing heard but a loud voice of tears. This generous young Lord ſaid then thus to him. <hi>Sir, do not weep;</hi> I <hi>had no deſign but to ſalute you; to thank you; and to beg pardon, as now</hi> I <hi>do, both of your ſelf, and in your perſon, at the hands of all thoſe who are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent here; deſiring them to learn at my coſt, and to pray for my Soul.</hi> This he ſaid with ſo ſtrong a voice, as that he was heard, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the noiſe of their weeping. I alſo was not able to ſtay my tears; when he, leaning towards mine ear, ſpake theſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words now below, as before he had done above: <hi>Behold, your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence is weeping; and yet ſtill you tell me</hi> I <hi>muſt have a Noble Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then having repeated divers times, <hi>In manus tuas Domine, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo ſpiritum meum;</hi> and, <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe me Domine, ſecundum eloqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:39290:71"/>tuum, &amp; non confundas me ab expectatione mea;</hi> he was wiſhed to aſcend and then to lay himſelf down upon the Scaffold. At the ſame inſtant one of the <hi>Conforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori</hi> ſaying to him, <hi>Cheerfully Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnor Troilo, couragiouſly Signor Troilo;</hi> and a whole cry of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers being raiſed and made by all the company for him, that vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Heart did anſwer even with a ſmiling countenance;<note n="a" place="margin">A noble, and holy valiant heart.</note> 
               <hi>Know</hi> (a) <hi>Gentlemen, that</hi> I <hi>dy cheerfully for the</hi> Love <hi>of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and in</hi> Penance <hi>for my ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he was laying down his head; <hi>where</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> And turning towards the <hi>Executioner,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Stay a while; for</hi> I <hi>will be reconciled.</hi> And beck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning me firſt towards him with his countenance; <hi>Father</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>on this hand</hi> I <hi>place my</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Theſe Saints he uſed as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſors for him to Chriſt our Lord.</note> Good Angel; <hi>and on that</hi> S. Paul, <hi>and</hi> S. John Baptiſt; our B. Lady <hi>ſhall ſtand before. Your Reverence
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:39290:71"/>muſt remember to perform the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you made me.</hi> I <hi>will ſay,</hi> O bone Jeſu eſto mihi Jeſus; <hi>O good Lord Jeſus, he thou a</hi> Jeſus <hi>to me; and when you ſhall ſee the cord is in cutting, you muſt ſay,</hi> Egote abſolvo, &amp;c. <hi>that ſo when</hi> I <hi>ſhall invoke the name of</hi> Jeſus, <hi>and you</hi> abſolve me; <hi>my ſoul may begin her journey from this body of mine towards heaven, by the mercy of my Lord, as</hi> I <hi>confide it ſhall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ingeniouſly confeſs I was ſo extremely amaz'd within my ſelf, and fell into ſuch an exceſs of weeping, that I had not a word to anſwer at the inſtant, but in the language of tears. And he, in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his head upon the block, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſpake theſe very words: <hi>Dear Father, draw near me. Let is ſuffice, and</hi> I <hi>take you to witneſs, That</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">So that his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and courage was far from fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there is hardly to be found in any hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of wiſdom, prudence of mind, magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and ſanctity.</note> I <hi>proteſt my ſelf in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to lay down a thouſand heads, in this one head of mine; and in this one life to offer up a thouſand
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:39290:72"/>lives.</hi> I <hi>accuſe my ſelf for not doing it with that fervour of devotion, that vehemency of Contrition, and that promptitude of reſignation, which</hi> I <hi>have been told and taught. But</hi> I <hi>know not how to do more.</hi> I <hi>accuſe my ſelf as truly of all the ſins</hi> I <hi>have confeſſed to your Reverence, as if now</hi> I <hi>did repeat them to you one by one. In</hi> Penance, <hi>if it pleaſe you,</hi> I <hi>will give my head to</hi> Chriſt <hi>as a puniſhment moſt deſerv'd by me; and of you</hi> I <hi>deſire</hi> Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>So did this Noble heart, which neither was, nor was to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd or danted, lay down that head upon the block. And ſaying then, <hi>Bring</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">See how this true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues even to the end, and in the end.</note> 
               <hi>hither the</hi> Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix <hi>that I may ſee it;</hi> he began alſo to ſay, <hi>O bone Jeſu, ſis mihi Jeſus; O good Lord Jeſus, be a Jeſus to me,</hi> being accompanied by all the people, who were already upon their knees, and who alſo invoked the name of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> And my ſelf
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:39290:72"/>ſtanding cloſe at the one ſide of his head, and looking ſtill when the <hi>Executioner</hi> would go about to cut the cord, as ſoon as I ſaw the knife lifted up for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I ſaid outright, <hi>Ego</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve thee from all thy ſins in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt.</note> 
               <hi>te abſolvo ab omnibus peccatis tuis in nomine Patris, &amp; Filii, &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Sancti, Amen.</hi> He did then both more ſpeedily and more loudly then was his cuſtom, ſay <hi>O Jeſu, ſis mihi Jeſus; O Jeſus, be thou a Jeſus to me.</hi> And at the inſtant, his head flew off at once, from his body, my ſelf, with many others alſo beholding that head thus ſeparated from the body, to produce the laſt ſyllable of the name JESUS, with a ſtrong kind of hiſs, or whiſper. And I doubt not but the Son flew up immediately into<note n="(f)" place="margin">His body was interred in the <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſa Nuova.</hi>
               </note> Heaven; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning all his former life with a moſt holy end; upon that very day of the year whereon the moſt Illuſtrious Lord his Father had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:39290:73"/>this life, before this Son of his was born; that being the eighteenth of <hi>April, Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> 1574. this the eighteenth of the ſame moneth. 1592.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:39290:73"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS. With an Explication of the ITALIANISMS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe hirth, perſon and parts of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man. <hi>pag. 5. &amp; 125</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Crimes, both Rapes and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. <hi>p. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Banditi</hi> in Italy are out-laws and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, condemned and proſcribed by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation (in that language termed <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi>) like our <hi>Moſs-troopers,</hi> or the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of Ireland. <hi>p. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Caſtle <hi>Sant Angelo,</hi> the chief Priſon in Rome. <hi>p. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>This ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned in the beginning of P. <hi>Clement 8.</hi> his Fontificate. <hi>p. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Theatins an Order of Religious perſons, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by <hi>John Peter Caraff,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Theate</hi> in Naples. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Mother became unwill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgly the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of her ſons reproachful death. <hi>p. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:39290:74"/>
               <item>The vanity of worldly pleaſure exhibited by a fit Emblem. <hi>p. 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The way of the Croſs is the moſt ſafe. <hi>p. 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefits of affliction. <hi>p. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The reſignation and humility of the noble Youth. <hi>p. 22,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The often confeſſing his ſins. <hi>p. 24, 25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſeveral manners of proceeding againſt Delinquents in other Countries compar'd with ours. <hi>p. 30, 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Fathers of the <hi>Chieſa Nova. 1.</hi> the new Church, are Prieſts of the Oratory of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> inſtituted by S. <hi>Philip Nereus. p. 39, 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How the young Lord behav'd himſelf when he receiv'd the firſt news of his death. <hi>p. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The manicling his hands. <hi>p 42.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The manner how he was met by the <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatori. 1.</hi> the Comforters. <hi>p. 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The firſt thing he did was to confeſs himſelf. <hi>p 44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Accepts of Gods providence with great ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity. <hi>p. 46.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Makes a declaration of his Faith. <hi>p. 47.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The pious Inſtructions, &amp; Communications of the <hi>Confortatori. p. 50, 51, 111, 114.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Will made, and the particulars of it. <hi>p. 52, 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:39290:74"/>
               <item>It muſt have ſeven witneſſes in Italy to make it valid. <hi>p 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How he diſpos'd his body. <hi>p. 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His admirable Contriti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. <hi>p. 60, 61, 69.70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His unſpeakable grief for his diſob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tance to his Mother. <hi>p. 63, 97, 117.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How ſhe educated him. <hi>p. 64 65.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Her invincible love and care of him. <hi>p. 67, 68, 69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His exact method in Confeſsing. <hi>p. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He did even melt between grief and love. <hi>p. 62.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His willingneſs to dy. <hi>p. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Puniſhment impos'd may be made voluntary by a voluntary acceptation of it. <hi>p. 83.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Devotions to his good Angel. <hi>p. 86, 87 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His ejaculatory Prayers. <hi>p 92.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He ſaid the Litanies and all the Fathers wept. <hi>p. 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Providitore</hi> in Italian ſignifies a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vider, but here it is tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for an Officer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng the <hi>Confor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atori della miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> or Sodality of mercy. <hi>p 43 64.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His laſt meſſage and recommendatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Mother. <hi>p 97 98.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To his Grandmother. <hi>p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>00.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:39290:75"/>
               <item>His humble meſſage to the Pope. <hi>p. 102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He found no trouble nor temptation in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>p. 112.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His dovout receiving the Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>p. 107.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His pious and prudent Anſwers to ſeveral queſtions. <hi>p. 115, 118.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Devotion to our B. Lady. <hi>p. 119.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Confortatori</hi> wept bitterly. <hi>p. 125.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He asked pardon of the Souldiers. <hi>p. 127.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Remarks of his admirable Carriage. <hi>p 128.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>He fell into an ardent weeping. <hi>p. 130.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For his ſins, not his death. <hi>p. 131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His great piety and gratitude. <hi>p. 132.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His words to the Executioner. <hi>p. 133.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A loud voice of tears among the Spectators. <hi>p. 139.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His chearfulneſs at the laſt moment. <hi>p. 135, 140.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His advice to the people. <hi>137.139.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The L. Governour wept paſsionately. <hi>p 138.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Troilo</hi>'s laſt jaculatory, Prayers. <hi>139 142</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His laſt words at the block. <hi>p. 144.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Ghoſtly Fathers tears. <hi>p. 141.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Execution. <hi>p. 143.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The death and burial of <hi>Signora Flaminia</hi> his Mother. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:39290:75"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page. 29. line 19. de le <hi>not,</hi> p. 41. l. 3. r <hi>B. Lady.</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. l. 3. p 6. r <hi>conſortat.</hi> p 27. l. 11. r <hi>from.</hi> off p. 58. l 74. r ones <hi>ſins.</hi> p. 65. l. 18 r <hi>particul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar.</hi> p. 67, l 2.3. r <hi>whereby,</hi> p. 59. l. 1. r <hi>comitted.</hi> p 62 l. 23. r might p. 83. l. 23. r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>night.</hi> p. 83. P. 91 l. 6. r occaſion. <hi>As.</hi> p. 95. in margin. r <hi>whole, ofice of.</hi> p. 1 26. l. 6. r <hi>peace.</hi> p. 1 18. l. 10. r <hi>ſaid he.</hi> p. 121. in mergin r <hi>entrance.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
